<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right devil discovered in his descent, form, education, qualification, place and nature of torment : with many other divine secrets, never as yet extant : published for confutation of the learned, instructing the wise, and undeceiving of the simple / written by Laur. Claxton.</title>
            <author>Claxton, Laurence, 1615-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12734871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12734871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">92988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 92988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1523:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right devil discovered in his descent, form, education, qualification, place and nature of torment : with many other divine secrets, never as yet extant : published for confutation of the learned, instructing the wise, and undeceiving of the simple / written by Laur. Claxton.</title>
                  <author>Claxton, Laurence, 1615-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by Francis Cossinet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: all after signature K7 lacking; pages stained, tightly bound and torn with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devil.</term>
               <term>Temptation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHT DEVIL DISCOVERED:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>In his Deſcent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>In his Form.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>In his Education.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>In his Qualification.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>In his Place and nature of Torment.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> With many other Divine Secrets, never as yet extant.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for Confutation of the Learned, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the Wiſe, and undeceiving of the ſimple.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Laur. Claxton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 8. 44.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye are of your father the devil, and the luſts of your father ye will do,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that committeth ſin, is of the devil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 John 3. 8, 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Coſſinet,</hi> at the Sign of the Anchor and Mariner in Tower-ſtreet, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
            <head>To you the Seed of Faith, the onely beloved Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the Lord of Glory, your poor deſpiſed Brother, yet heir with you of that immortal endleſs kingdom, ſaluteth you as followeth:</head>
            <p>IN this Treatiſe I have brought to publique view your grand Oppoſite <hi>Cain,</hi> the father of all the devils children, in which you may take full ſight of his majeſtical perſon in this his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with all his glory appertaining to him; therefore you that are not onely verbally, but really the Seed of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſing praiſes to Chriſt your Savior, that your treaſure is not laid up in this kingdom that ſhall periſh and have an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and becauſe of poverty here, rejoyce that your riches is in your kingdom yet to come; mourn not becauſe of hatred here, for this kingdom loves its own; let this rejoyce your ſouls, that every day you are nearer your Journeys end, and let this elevate your ſpirits, that before you be aware, the Lord whom ye love &amp; have long look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, is a coming, and will wipe away all tears from your eyes, and ſorrows from your hearts; for believe it, the Lord hath recorded all your
<pb facs="tcp:92988:3"/> enemies in his breſt, and will execute vengeance upon them; therefore fear not the credit of this world, not the loſs of thy life for thy God, but rejoyce thou haſt power over thy corruptions, I ſay rejoyce for evermore, for our God doth love an upright innocent ſoul; therefore take heed of hypocriſie, and deceive not thy ſelf in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a perſonal God, and hateſt to be reformed, for it is life eternal, not onely to be a profeſſor, but a poſſeſſor; this is the <hi>White Stone</hi> and <hi>Hidden M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nna,</hi> that hath ſo few, and no name, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ow what I ſay; therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not that firſt of <hi>John</hi> 3. 17. I ſay remember upon what account, and to whom I ſpeak it, otherwiſe at the laſt day thou ſhalt finde thoſe ſayings in <hi>Matthew</hi> 25. 34, &amp;c. fall heavy upon thee.</p>
            <p>Now who ever ſhall peruſe this Epiſtle, and hath a deſire to read one thing more then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then caſt thy eye upon this enſuing <hi>Index,</hi> and there from Page 1 to 20, and ſo on, thou ſhalt finde by the Figures, what thou moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in; and the Lord give thee underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, and faith to obſerve it. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>YOu have the Introduction of the miraculous Convert.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CAP. I.</head>
               <item>II. <hi>The firſt deſcent and true form of the right Devil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</hi> From page 1 to 20.</item>
               <item>III. <hi>Certain notable Queries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>wered.</hi> from p. 20 to 34</item>
               <item>IV. <hi>The Righteous Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> finde few rich men ſaved, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Seed of Faith ſhall be rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> p. 34 to 49</item>
               <item>V. <hi>The difference of rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from 49 to 54</item>
               <item>VI. <hi>The right dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from 54 to 65</item>
               <item>VII. <hi>The devil th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>preted.</hi> from 65 to 76</item>
               <item>VIII. <hi>None but the Seed of F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>h underſtand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> from 76 to 81</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CAP. II.</head>
               <item>IX. <hi>No Saint educated like the devil.</hi> from 81 to 87</item>
               <item>X. <hi>Not onely a rich, but a poor devil.</hi> from 87 to 91</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CAP. III.</head>
               <item>XI. <hi>The light ranting devils quality.</hi> from 91 to 100</item>
               <item>XII. <hi>The dark ranting devils quality.</hi> from 100 to 108</item>
               <item>XIII. <hi>The covetous devils quality.</hi> from 108 to 114</item>
               <item>XIV. <hi>The vaſt difference of the two ſeeds in death.</hi> from 114 to 116</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>CAP. IV.</head>
               <item>XV. <hi>The Saint-like moderate devils quality.</hi> from 116 to 123</item>
               <item>XVI. <hi>The maner of Chriſts coming to judgement.</hi> from 123 to 127</item>
               <item>XVII. <hi>The place where the devils ſhall be tormented.</hi> from 127 to 130</item>
               <item>XVIII. <hi>The nature of the devils torment.</hi> from 130 to the end.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:92988:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>ABout the firſt of <hi>February</hi> 1657. I took my journey for <hi>London,</hi> for the accompliſhing of a place then in agitation, and at my arrival there, I was informed that the two Witneſſes that I had often read of in <hi>Revelation</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, was now to be ſeen and ſpoken withal, unto whom I forthwith applied my ſelf to hear what they could ſay for themſelves; then thinking in my ſelf, there was none in mortal fleſh able to maintain an argument with me, as to thoſe fundamentals by them publiſhed to the world, <hi>viz.</hi> God, Devil, Heaven, Hell, Angels, and the mortality of the Soul; but, alas! when I came to <hi>John Reeve,</hi> ſo ſtyled the Prophet of the Lord, which at that time I could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and obſerved his poſition then ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:92988:5"/> unto me, which was this, Did I know the form, nature, and eſſence of God? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of cavelling or improving the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of reaſon, with which I was well guarded, I was admiring that word <hi>Form,</hi> how it was poſsible God ſhould admit of a Form: to which I replyed, deſiring to know what maner of Form he had. His anſwer was, God was in Form of a man, clearer then Chryſtal, brighter then the Sun, ſwifter then thought: Then was my ſoul the more troubled, that God being a man, ſhould be ſwifter then thought; This I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, it was requiſite God ſhould be ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thought, but God having a Form, I could not underſtand how he ſhould be ſwifter then thought; well notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I was not ſatisfied, yet at that time little did I ſay, onely took his book along with me, and to my Chamber I went, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing his writing, in which I found ſuch heavenly Myſteries, that the eyes nor ears of mortal fleſh had never writ, ſeen, or heard the like before; ſo that now began the travel of my ſoul, how I ſhould own
<pb facs="tcp:92988:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> this unparallel'd truth, and hold my Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which was the onely livelihood of my ſelf and five children, conſulting with my reaſon, it would be well if I could injoy both; and to that end I endeavored my ſelf, and to my Benefice went again, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving my parts as formerly, but the more I labored to preſerve my ſelf under that goard of above an hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> the more the beams of the eternal God did ſcorch and wither my ſhadow of reſt.</p>
               <p>Yea, preſently after there came in me a mighty conflict which did ſift; turn, yea, ſearch the whole man in me, inſomuch that I was as it were in a warlike poſture, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I had beſt yeeld up my Benefice, or hold it at a venture; but then, even then, was I ſummoned to give an account of my Stewardſhip, how I had ſpent my life this forty years, and what I did think would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of my Soul, and what would thy riches and glory here avail thee in the grave, but eſpecially at the great day of account?</p>
               <p>Now friends, I would have you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:92988:6"/> that I was in a ſtrait betwixt two, ſo that out of hand the ſpirit of Faith pleaded thus in me, That I had no Commiſsion to preach, and forthwith muſt ceaſe, though it was to the loſs of my hundred pound a year; then ſtept in the ſpirit of reaſon, and pleaded, How ſhall my ſelf, with five children ſubſiſt, when as this Benefice would comfortably and honorably provide for us during life. Then, even then, was death and life ſet before me, and the ſpirit of Faith pleaded thus within me, That whether I had rather injoy my Benefice, and therein live honorably in this world, and ſo be damned to all eternity in the world to come, or whether I would hearken to that call within me, to forſake my preaching with the benefit thereof, and truſt the Lord with my ſelf and the children? this lay hard upon me, and ſo narrowly purſued me, that for the ſpace of three weeks I could not be at quiet ſleeping nor waking, going nor riding, in which time I had no little conflict to diſown the glory of this world, for the glory of God, ſuppoſing my conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:92988:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be ſafe and ſecure as any man or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Prieſt in the world whatſoever; and for my doctrine, I was not inferior to any, but more able to declare the truth which I apprehended to be truth, then the beſt of them.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, all this would do me no good, nor in the leaſt ſilence this combate within me, but I muſt ceaſe my trade of preaching, leſt a worſe thing befall me; and at that inſtant it came in my thoughts, Remember me, how here in this world where now thou liveſt, I was a poor deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, though now a rich immortal glorious God; and therefore take no care, I will provide for thee and thine, ſo far as is requiſite for ſuch a one as thou art to be; and withal remember when thou waſt in thy wickedneſs, not knowing me, then I provided for thee, How much more now ſhall I be mindful of thee ſo far as ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thy good: Many of theſe refreſhings did ariſe from my ſeed-ſpring within me, that I was made willing to diſown all, that not long before I had taken great pains to
<pb facs="tcp:92988:7"/> perfect, and ſo in ſubmitting to the true light, darkneſs fled, and the Lord freely forgave me all that was paſt, preſent, and to come, and hath every week more and more enabled me to walk obedient and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right before him, mortifying ſin continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within me, to the onely praiſe of my God be it ſpoken, that my calling and election is ſo firm and ſure, that I vveigh not the cenſure of men nor Angels, but as ſure as Chriſt is the eternal God, I ſhall at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance reign eternally vvith him in the heavens; and though in my journey to my bed of ſleep, the grave, inſtead of riches, I ſhall meet with poverty; inſtead of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, want; inſtead of honor, diſhonor; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of love, hatred; inſtead of a good name, all maner of evil tearms; inſtead of friends, foes; yea, may be ſuch as will perſecute me to the graves mouth, yet now all this I matter not, in that ſin is my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and Chriſt is my Maſter, whom my ſoul earneſtly craves more knowledge of himſelf, with aſsiſtance of his power to withſtand the deſpiſers of thy perſon ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:92988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Now ſince the Lord in his own time, hath in his free mercy called and choſen me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his eternal purpoſe of old, that I ſhould redeem the time, I have loſt forty years, and for the future, the ſhort time I have to ſtay in this preſent evil world, my God, I doubt not, will enable me to walk holy and without blame before him till I be called to ſleep, or the day of his appearance change this my poor mortal, to that immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal like himſelf, either of which it ſhall pleaſe my God of mercy in his own time and pleaſure to call me unto, I had rather enjoy, then now at this preſent [mark what I ſay] then now at this preſent, enjoy all the riches and wiſdom that ever God gave to <hi>Solomon;</hi> ſo that I can boldly ſay, Happy, yea, thrice happy am I that the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> that lying murthering devil who captivated my ſoul many years a ſervant to ſin, and all maner of evil, is now diſarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſilent in me, and in room thereof the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> that bleſſed ſeed of Faith, hath got the victory, by which I am deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the power of the fruits of fleſh,
<pb facs="tcp:92988:8"/> and tranſlated to the fruits of the ſpirit of Faith, in the perſon of Chriſt the onely true and everliving God.</p>
               <p>After this my remarkable change, being at home, ſilent and quiet in this my mortal tabernacle, I was powerfully commanded, yea my ſeed-ſpring hath certain times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited me to demonſtrate to publike view, that point concerning the Devil; which very title or name Devil, doth fright the Devil himſelf, and the ground of this his fear, doth ariſe from the non-knowledge of his firſt riſe, the deſcription of his form, as alſo his education and qualification, with the place and nature of his torment: thy ignorance in theſe things, hath produced matter ſufficient for my Genius to recal thy thoughts, as touching thy miſtake of the right Devil, and ſo according as the true onely wiſe God hath revealed in me, <hi>I</hi> ſhall make known theſe in their order, which hath not yet been branched forth, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:92988:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CAP. I. The firſt deſcent and true Form of the right Devil, diſcovered.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <p>FIrſt, as touching the Devil, his riſe and original, I ſhall infallibly make known unto thee, and from inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhew, that ſubtile beaſt or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent there ſpoken of, was no horned beaſt or creeping Serpent, as the Prieſts vainly teach; neither was it any Pippin or Pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, or any other ſort of Apple that was ſo pleaſant in <hi>Eves</hi> eye, or delightful to her taſte: No, no, it was that reprobate glorious Angel, that was far more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ſweeter to <hi>Eves</hi> taſte then the ſweeteſt fruit whatſoever: therefore I ſhall demand of the proudeſt of his ſeed now living, what was, or which now of all creatures or things in this world, is moſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:92988:9"/> pleaſant in thy eyes, or moſt in thy ſoul deſiring to taſte? Art thou a man, then is not a woman beautified and richly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, moſt pleaſant in thy eyes, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to thy taſte? Art thou a woman, what ſaith thou, is not a man beautified and richly atired with ſubtile and ſophiſtical expreſſions, moſt pleaſant in thy eyes, and ſooneſt deceived by him?</p>
                  <p>Even ſo that reprobate Angelical man, was that ſubtile Serpent or beaſt of the field; minde what you read, that angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was ſo pleaſant to her taſte, that ſhe took it, and did eat, which is no more then this, That proud, beautiful, glorious angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, did by his ſeeming divine wiſdom and Angelical perſon, bewitch <hi>Eves</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſoul to hearken unto him, and her eyes to dote upon him, that ſhe admitted him enterance into her body, in which, and by which ſhe found ſo much delight (that after that) ſhe inticed her husband, who had copulation with <hi>Eve,</hi> as man with woman in theſe days; ſo her innocent ſoul and body being defiled by that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:92988:9"/> Dragon-angel, after which her husband <hi>Adam</hi> going in unto her, was alſo defiled, as a ſound woman ſhould receive into her body a diſeaſed man, not onely her womb is defiled, but ſhe pollutes her husband alſo; as the Pox or Gangreen doth eat throughout the whole man, ſo <hi>Eves</hi> ſoul and body being defiled, did pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie the ſeed of <hi>Adam:</hi> From hence it was there came two ſeeds, the one pure, the other impure, the one righteous, the other wicked; Inſtance, from the womb of <hi>Rebecca</hi> came two ſeeds at one travel, bleſſed <hi>Jacob,</hi> and curſed <hi>Eſau;</hi> thus in plainneſs of termes, I have in ſhort writ to plain ſober-hearted men.</p>
                  <p>But now from the words of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, I muſt ſpeak to the ſeed of Faith, that innocent ſoul-ſaved generation, and that becauſe the learned of this periſhing world cannot believe, though an Angel ſhould ſpeak from heaven, as you the ſeed of the Lord ſhall hear that ſeed of this Serpent will hiſs, yea, if poſſible; ſting from his venemous tongue, this infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:92988:10"/> interpretation of theſe enſuing words; <hi>But of the tree of knowledge of good and evil thou ſhalt not eat of it, for in the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> Now if you look into the third of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> with an eye of Faith, then you may clearly ſee what that Tree of Knowledge of good and evil did ſignifie: The words are theſe, <hi>And the Serpent ſaid to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ye ſhall not ſurely die, for God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods knowing good and evil: And when the Woman ſaw that the Tree was good for food, and that it was pleaſant to the eyes, and a Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſhe took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave alſo unto her husband, and he did eat.</hi> Oh my ſpiritual brethren, in that my ſoul deſireth your perfection as my own, therefore I would gladly have you poſſeſſed with an infallible underſtanding between <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, and the Dragon and his Angels, or between the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:92988:10"/> the Serpent: Why? becauſe in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe two diſtinct ſeeds, ſons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> generations, depends a general under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the ſpirit of the Scriptures; therefore let thy ear wait on thy eye, and thy heart on both, for now I ſhall unlock that ſecret Cabinet that hath not been opened ſince the creation till this laſt Witneſs; therefore attend and take notice that it is a general opinion amongſt learned men, that the Serpent which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto <hi>Eve,</hi> was one of the beaſts of the field which the Lord God had made, and that the devil was an inviſible ſpirit which entred into the body of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſpake thoſe ſubtile ſpeeches through his mouth, and ſo cauſed the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to eat of the fruit of the natural Tree which the Lord God had forbidden, and tempting her husband to eat of that fruit with her, it operated that venomous evil in them, and all mankinde. <hi>[Note]</hi> Oh the groſs darkneſs that poſſeſſeth the learned men of this periſhing world, you know that the Scriptures are generally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:92988:11"/> in natural terms, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of ſpiritual things to the weak comprehenſion of ſinful mortals, and yet notwithſtanding, the natural wiſdom of this world would perſwade men to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them exactly in the letter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they meaſure the glorious things of eternity by their rational learning onely, as aforeſaid; but to enlighten thy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, minde Scripture-records, how that Chriſt is called a Lyon, a Lamb, a Stone, a Door, a Way, a Vine, a green Tree, and ſuch like expreſſions in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto ſpiritual meanings; alſo you may read evil-minded men are ſometimes called by the names of Devils, Dragons, Vipers, Serpents, Dogs, Swines, fruitleſs Trees, and ſuch like, according to that of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, when he ſaid, <hi>Now the ax is laid to the root of the Tree, every Tree therefore that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down and caſt into the fire:</hi> So likewiſe you that are ſpiritual, may know that, yea, that Angelical re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, by whom <hi>Eve</hi> was deceived,
<pb facs="tcp:92988:11"/> was called a Dragon, an old Serpent, the Devil and Satan, a Deceiver, or the Tree of knowledge of good and evil; and ſuch like names ſuteable unto his curſed nature; ſo that the naked truth is this, that Serpent that tempted <hi>Eve,</hi> was that Angelical Dragon-devil beforeſaid, which the Lord God from the higheſt heavens caſt down to the loweſt earth, where there, as beforeſaid, he bewitched <hi>Eves</hi> innocent ſoul; for if you know what you read, you ſhall finde three prevalent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments perſwading her to conſent unto the Serpents language:
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The Tree was good for meat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>It was pleaſant to the eyes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>It was to be deſired to make one wiſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before I write of the three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets hid in the Angelical temptation, give me leave to ſpeak a little of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the ſecret wiſdom of God to his choſen ones: You that are of the ſeed of Faith, and none but you, doth know that in the Divine will of the infinite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, there is a twofold operation, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:92988:12"/> is this, minde what thou readeſt, this is a great myſtery, When the wiſdom of God ſeeth fit to reveal a Divine ſecret to his own ſeed, then his holy Spirit is all active, and when he ſeeth fit to obſcure it from them, then his Divine Spirit is all paſſive: Why? becauſe for the manifeſtation of his infinite power and wiſdom, that he can create light out of darkneſs, yea life out of death with a glorious advantage: For underſtand this, that if the glorious Creator, for the tryal of his creature, ſhould leave the moſt experimental man that is, to his own inſpired light, and ſuffer him to be tempted to that evil of murther or adultery, &amp; overcome thereby, he muſt of neceſſity loſe that former joy and peace of the divine light or love of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n him, and in the room thereof, both ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd feel nothing but ſpiritual darkneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith a ſecret fear of eternal death, until <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he light of life appears again, with a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſurance of a glorious deliverance from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat ſinful darkneſs and fearful death, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>foreſaid; truly whatever man ſhall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:92988:12"/> to the contrary, as ſure as there is a God, this was the condition of both <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> when they were defiled with unlawful luſt one towards another, by that ſubtile temptation of that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents counſel, called the Tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evil.</p>
                  <p>Again, though it is ſaid, It was a Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, yet you may know that the ſoul of <hi>Eve</hi> was not of a deſiring nature after wiſdom in her creation, becauſe ſhe was all divine ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in her ſelf, therefore that deſire of taſting of the fruit of a Tree, to make her wiſe as Gods, to know both good and evil, proceeded onely from the rational nature of an unſatisfied ſpirit of the Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Serpent; for this I would have you to underſtand, that at that time when <hi>Eve</hi> was tempted to evil by the Serpent, ſhe was wholly left to her own ſtrength, &amp; it was the ſeeming glory of his Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal language that over-topped her preſent light, and begot that deſire in her under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, through which her ſoul was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:92988:13"/> with a powerful deſire to make tryal of his Serpentine counſel, and to taſte of his ſpiritual meat, ſo highly exalted by him: Why? becauſe to her received new thoughts, ſhe had not heard ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a language before. <hi>Alſo the Tree was pleaſant for ſight;</hi> yet before that glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Serpent appeared, <hi>Eve</hi> wanted no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in beholding the man <hi>Adam,</hi> but ſhe looking a little too long upon the comlineſs of his form, through his infuſed Witchcraft, her ſoul was raviſht through his Angelical perſon.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>it was a Tree whoſe fruit was to be deſired to make one wiſe as Gods, to know both good and evil:</hi> Now minde the pretended meaning of the ſerpent in thoſe words, was this, If ſhe did but taſte of the fruit of that Tree, it was ſo full of divine vertue, that ſhe could not only be like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, but ſhe would be as a God to her ſelf, alſo to know all that was to be known, whether good or evil, within her own ſoul; but the truth is, the Serpents ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intent was this, that when ſhe had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:92988:13"/> taſted of that forbidden fruit, ſhe ſhould with him both know and feel in her own ſpirit, the difference between light and darkneſs, life and death, love and envy, peace and war, good and evil, or God and devil; likewiſe obſerve ſince <hi>Eve,</hi> the natural mother of all man-kinde, was overcome by luſt, through the ſubtilty of the Serpent, hath not many a poor inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent virgin, or virgin-wife in like maner been deceived through the comelineſs of mens perſons, and their Serpentine lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, by perſwading them that they loved them above their own lives, and of giving them ſuch content they know not of; or if they deny them, it will be their death, yea, telling them, All men are but one man, and all women are but one woman, and therefore it is purity to be free unto all, and that they are in the greateſt bondage which are united unto one onely; I ſay, hath not theſe, and ſuch like curſed counſels, occaſioned many innocent ſoul to betray their virginity, or virgin-bed unto their perpetual ſorrow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:92988:14"/> and ſhame afterwards; Juſt thus was it with the virgin-wife <hi>Eve,</hi> though it may ſeem ſtrange at the firſt unto many that ſhall read this Epiſtle; yet you know the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That ſhe ſeeing the Tree good for meat, and pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, took of the fruit thereof, and did eat;</hi> that is, When the innocent ſoul of <hi>Eve</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered with the Serpents ſubtile lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as beforeſaid, her ſpirit did conſent unto him to come in unto her, and take full poſſeſſion of her, to be her God and guide in ſtead of her Creator: Truly in this caſe the Virgin <hi>Eve's</hi> condition may fitly be compared unto the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> for you know after the Angel had told her, that without knowing of man, ſhe ſhould be with childe, through the power of the moſt High overſhadowing of her, how eaſily was ſhe intreated, not onely to have it ſo, but alſo how exceedingly did her ſoul rejoyce with the very tidings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Again, if men look with a ſpiritual eye between their Angelical ſalutations,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:92988:14"/> you may ſee more ſeeming glorious injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the unclean angel greeting of Eve, then in the holy Angels ſaluting of <hi>Mary:</hi> Again, though men or Angels ſhould gainſay it, from the ſpirit of truth it ſelf, I ſhall declare the very ſenſe of this ſecret in plainneſs of ſpeech [which was this] As ſoon as ever Eves innocent ſoul, through the permiſſive power of God was overcome to conſent to the Serpents cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed councel, his Angelical perſon entered into her womb through her ſecret parts, and being united to her ſoul and body, his ſerpentine nature diſſolved it ſelf into her pure ſeed, and defiled her throughout, and ſo became eſſentially one with her; through which naturally ſhe conceived a Serpent Dragon devil, into a man child of fleſh, blood and bone; and brought forth her firſt begotten ſon of the Devil, yea the very Dragon, ſerpent, devil himſelf, and called his name, according to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Cain,</hi> or curſed, though ignorantly ſhe ſaid ſhe had received a man from the Lord: So likewiſe on the contrary, the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:92988:15"/> womb of the Virgin-wife <hi>Mary</hi> was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored with the onely wiſe Angelical God himſelf, through which her polluted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was not onely cleanſed whilſt he was in her womb, but alſo by vertue of the Divine power, ſhe was enabled to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his glorious majeſty of her ſeed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a holy Babe of unſpotted fleſh, blood and bone, and in his ſeaſon to bring forth her firſt begotten Son of God, and call his name, according to his nature, <hi>Emmanuel, Jeſus,</hi> or <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> ſo that you which are truely and inwardly baptized with the true knowledge of the holy One of Iſrael, may ſee in ſome meaſure what is meant by the two Scripture-ſeeds, the Angelical devil firſt became a man-child, and the Angelical God afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a man-child: thus the moſt holy God abaſed himſelf in the very womb of a woman, that he might firſt or laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the power of that ſerpentine reaſon, or lying imagination in all his elect Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:92988:15"/>
                  <p>Thus, if you be not ſtone-blind, you may clearly ſee that the ſerpentine angel when he tempted <hi>Eve,</hi> was no homely beaſt, as men vainly imagine from their beaſtly reaſon, but he was a ſpiritual body, and appeared unto <hi>Eve</hi> in form like unto a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God or man. Now if you be unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied as touching the Angelical ſerpent, conſiſting of as large a compaſs as the perſon of a man, and yet could enter into the womb of Eve through ſo narrow a paſſage, as is declared by me; I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee in thoſe ſayings of <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> the third, where he ſaith, <hi>How can a man be born when he is old, can he enter the ſecond time into his mothers womb, and be born again?</hi> As our Lord anſwered <hi>Nicodemus</hi> unto his fleſhly que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſo likewiſe from his own light in like maner, I ſhall make anſwer unto this: Though the body of the Angelical Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in his length or breadth was as a man is, yet you may know it was not of a groſs ſubſtance as man is, but it was a ſpiritual body created in another world, for though
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:92988:16"/> the bodies of the mighty Angels are in forms like men, yet you may know that they ſhine like unto the Sun or a flame of fire, being formed in a Region of a more higher nature then this, therefore they are of motion more ſwifter then thought, &amp; of a pure, thin, or bright fiery nature; ſo that with great eaſe they pierce through a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row paſſage, at the divine pleaſure of the Creator: So likewiſe it was with that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent tree of knowledge of good and evil, for though his created purity was become all maner of imaginary impurities, through his outcaſt condition, yet you may know that his form was of a more fiery brightneſs then that of <hi>Adam,</hi> or elſe <hi>Eve</hi> could not poſſibly have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by him, as aforeſaid; alſo his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being ſpiritual, though his nature was carnal, there was no let to hinder this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into her womb, to bring forth the Creators ſecret purpoſe of two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, coming through the loins of one woman, to make an everlaſting diſtinction between the tranſcendent glory of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:92988:16"/> and ſhame of rejection.</p>
                  <p>Again, though the Angelical Serpent deſcended into the womb of <hi>Eve,</hi> yet you may know that his aſcending nature was utterly loſt; ſo that in ſtead of his aſcending upward into that habitation of raviſhing glory, from whence he was caſt, he was ignorant of it, and of that God and his mighty Angels, as if he had never known them in the leaſt; therefore he imagined his ſerpentine ſubtilty, to be the onely wiſdom then in being, and this world to be the onely heaven: Thus all the ſeed of Faith may be ſatisfied, that the Devil that was, is, or at the reſurrection ſhall ſo riſe, is in the form of a man, and this <hi>Cain,</hi> man-devil, in proceſs of time, married and begat ſons and daughters, ſo that there ſhall not onely be a male, but female devils alſo; yea, ſince there hath been, and now is legions, yea millions of legions of his ſeed, in the forms of men and women, and that as comely perſons as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver were born of a woman. O then ye ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> look about you, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:92988:17"/> lay to heart, how raſhly it hath, and now at this day is preached, and by you believed, that the devil was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man was created, as alſo that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil had never the form or ſhape of a man, but as it pleaſed Maſter Painter to draw him forth in ſuch a form, that when the devil knows himſelf to be a devil, thou wilt ſee the cheat of both the Limner and his Picture.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding it hath been infallibly proved, that there is no other devil but what is in men and women, yet it is made known unto me the various pleas and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes (why, or wherefore) the generation of <hi>Cain</hi> have endeavored to finde out a devil before, and without man: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which is a devil, is in antipathy to God, ſo a profeſſed enemy to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſon; alſo the very name devil, is a frightful curſed name, a name that is a terror to all ſober-minded men; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to cloke their curſed deviliſh actions, and that they may not be noted by the righteous <hi>Abels</hi> to be devils, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:92988:17"/> generation atribute it to a devil without them.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, It is by them ſuppoſed, the devil is a deformed creature, of an ugly ſhape, with a cloven foot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore, ſay they, it cannot be a man or woman, for they are comely, beautiful creatures.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It is by them believed, that the devil can transform himſelf into any form, and appear, where, how and when he pleaſeth; therefore it cannot be that man ſhould be the devil, in that man can do none of theſe things.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, ſay they, The devil is in hell tormented, and torments all that he can captivate in his bounds, but we are upon the earth, not tormented, neither torment we any man.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, ſay they, The devil is a wicked curſed blaſphemer againſt Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and all that is good, yea the devil is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, murthering perſecutor of the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of God; therefore it cannot be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> man ſhould be this devil, in that he is a true worſhipper of God, and is reverent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:92988:18"/> of his name, no blaſphemer, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of his people.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly and laſtly, The greateſt Appeal the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> can make for himſelf, is this, If there be no other devil but what is in men and women, then, ſay they, Kings may be devils, Magiſtrates devils, Merchants devils, Lawyers devils, Soldiers devils, Doctors devils, and Preachers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and ſo in concluſion there may be few other in this world that at the day of judgement ſhall be raiſed, but devils.</p>
                  <p>From theſe and ſuch like, hath that proud ſpirit of Reaſon in them corruptly imagined a Devil after their own fancy, and have chriſtened him <hi>Devil,</hi> yea, and given him a place of abode, either under the earth, in the hollow of the earth, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e depth of the waters, or in the air, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e place they know not where; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this is becauſe they would not have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od nor his people take notice that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e his ſeed: Theſe and ſuch like, are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome meaſure ſatisfactory to the ſpirit of Reaſon, that there is a devil without them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:92988:18"/> beſides them, and contrary to mans form.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding, it hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently maintained, nay, againſt all Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers proved, what the firſt deſcent or riſe of the Devil was, which never any ſince the foundation of the world could reveal till this Laſt Witneſs; yet for thy further ſatisfaction, I ſhall in ſhort anſwer thoſe thy frivolous Pleas and Excuſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt thou pleadeſt, <hi>The devil is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed creature, of an ugly ſhape, with a cloven foot,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is one of the imagined whimſies of the ignorant and learned in theſe days; this is one of the Scar-crows and Bug-bears believed, and ſo reported by his own ſeed, that the devil cannot be a man, in that he is a deformed beaſt; and yet not any of you dare avouch unto me where, when, and in what ſhape thou ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him, but in that thy ſoul is clothed with that ignorant dark devil within thee, thou apprehendeſt and imagineſt ſtrange appearances without thee, inſomuch that an old Tree in the night is ſuppoſed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:92988:19"/> unto thee: where this ignorance of a true God and a right devil hath taken place, oh how fearful is that ſoul of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without it, when the riſe of thy fear is really within thee! As conſider, what is the cauſe that a ſoul cries out, <hi>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the devil ſtands before me, waiting to carry me away with him,</hi> and all that are with thee beholds nothing but thy ſelf frighted and tormented by the devil within thee? for my ſeed-ſpring declares unto thee, there is no ſuch thing as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by thee; but that devil that ever was, is, or ſhall be, is for the moſt part as comely a creature as walks in <hi>London</hi> ſtreets, and hath as neat a foot and a a hand as any Lady in the land, which ſhall appear more at large in that Chapter that treats of the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> his educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or bringing up.</p>
                  <p>Again, It is by the Seed of <hi>Cain</hi> belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved man is not the devil, <hi>in that,</hi> ſaith thou, <hi>the devil can transform himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any form, and appear how, where, and when he pleaſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:92988:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If this were true, as it is not, it were nothing advantagious unto thee, in that I can in truth and reality inſtance one remarkable Devil-man now living, whoſe name is <hi>John Robins,</hi> that did more deviliſh exployts then any conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed devil without thee: Sometimes he did preſent the form of his perſon riding upon the wings of the winde, like unto a flame of fire; alſo he did preſent unto ſome in their beds a great light, like unto a flame of fire over all the room, that they have been compelled to hide their faces in their beds, fearing they ſhould be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but when they hid their faces in their beds, the light did appear more brighter then before: alſo he would preſent unto them Half-moons and Stars, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thick Darkneſs, darker then any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural darkneſs whatſoever: alſo he did preſent in the day time his head onely without a body, to a Gentlewoman in her chamber, preſenting unto her, to deceive her, the forms of ſtrange beaſts, as namely dragons, and ſuch like: much more might
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:92988:20"/> be ſpoken of his deceits in this kind, how many great lying ſigns and wonders this prince of devils was acted forthfar beyond all his curſed ſeed, though a great many more hath aſſumed to raiſe various ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, yet notwithſtanding all this the fundamental was in themſelves; as thus, A real devil within them, but an imagined devil without them; and thus their conſciences being ſeared, they ſeek to make others in faith with them, that they can raiſe a devil without them, which at the great day they ſhall finde it to be a cheat that ſhall burn in their ſouls and bodies more hotter then any fire and brimſtone.</p>
                  <p>Again, thou ſayeſt, <hi>The devil is in hell tormented, and torments all that he can captivate in his bounds, but we are on the earth not tormented,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This thy plea thou haſt received from others as wiſe as thy ſelf, that knows no more of a hell without man, then of a heaven within man; for alas poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſoul, thou apprehendſt a devil thou
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:92988:20"/> knows not what, and a hell thou knows not where, for the learned or the proudeſt of his ſeed little think or can believe, that their body ſhall be their hell, and their ſpirit or ſoul ſhall be their devil, ſhut up cloſe priſoners on this earth tormented to all eternity? neither ſhall you the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> believe that your cheats, oppreſſion, adultery, ſwearing, drunkenneſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting this infallible truth, with all other of your filthineſs, ſhall be that fuel that ſhall burn more hotter then any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fire in this world? And as touching that, whereas thou ſaith, <hi>We are upon the earth not tormented.</hi> Alas pititous ſoul! though all the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> are not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented alike, by reaſon of long habit and cuſtom, through which thy conſcience is ſeared, that no ſmall ſin will torment thee, but there are thouſands of thy brood that have an earneſt peny of that they ſhall be hereafter; otherwiſe what cauſeth the hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, doleful ſighs, groans and cries of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your ſeed in health, but much more on thy bed of ſickneſs, concluding in thy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:92988:21"/> ſelf, I am damned, I am damned to all eternity, finding in thy ſelf no peace, in that thou knows not the God of peace, neither haſt thou walked uprightly in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others as thou would they ſhould do to thee, but have either publickly or privately tranſgreſſed the Law, by which thy ſin is ſtrengthened, for the ſtrength of ſin is the law; and ſo death which is the ſting of ſin, arraigns thee at the bar of thy own conſcience, reading within thy own ſoul, all thy private evils againſt God and man, nay from my ſeed-ſpring I ſpeak it, many of this curſed ſeed are ſeemingly Saints, and do live as a people that doth righteous things, and in gifts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, heaven-like praying and preaching, to the admiration of all that hears them, and yet they find in themſelves, if they would ſpeak the truth, what ſad torments they undergo while they live on this earth, yea ſo great in ſome that their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot ceaſe till the ſoul make away it ſelf: As touching this I ſhall remind you of one remarkable accident, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:92988:21"/> many in <hi>London</hi> this day can witneſs the truth of what I write, <hi>Thomas Gun</hi> by name was the man, who for gifts and parts in the Miniſtry, as alſo for a civil life, did equalize all the teachers of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, if not excell them, and yet at that very ſame inſtant was guilty of adultery, and that for a long time deceived his own ſoul and the poor woman, his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for which could not be ſatisfied till he took a Piſtol and ſhot himſelf to death: thus it was with him, and ſo with many more little or much, are in hell, yea on this earth tormented, though nothing comparable to what thou ſhalt be at the day of Chriſts next appearance.</p>
                  <p>Again, thou ſayeſt, <hi>The devil is a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed curſed blaſphemer againſt God and all that is good, yea the devil is a lying mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering perſecutor of the people of God, therefore man is not the devil, becauſe he is a true worſhipper of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> If thou underſtoodſt what thou ſayeſt, I could ſet to my ſeal, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a true worſhipper of God, is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:92988:22"/> for indeed none can worſhip him, or be reverent of his name, but thoſe that are of the ſeed of Faith, thoſe that are eternally preſerved in peace here, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter; for it is life eternal to know thee the onely true God, without which knowledge, none can worſhip him, or be reverent of his name; thus far I agree and ſet to my ſeal, that this man is no devil: but alas, how many of theſe are in this periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing world, though millions of thouſand thouſands make a ſhow and a talk of a God, yet very few there are that knows him as he is, a glorious perſonal God, ſo that true was that ſaying from the Lord in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 10. 22. <hi>For though my people be as the ſand of the ſea, yet a remnant of them ſhal be ſaved: Fear not my little flock, it is your fathers pleaſure to give you a Kingdom: One of a tribe, two of a City;</hi> ſo few are thoſe that knows the true God, that they are but a handful to them that knows him not. But now to the Query in hand, <hi>The devil,</hi> ſaith thou, <hi>is a wicked curſed blaſphemer againſt God and all that</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:92988:22"/> 
                     <hi>is good;</hi> from whence thou concludes man cannot be this devil, in that man is not ſo wicked as to curſe and blaſpheme God; what if I can find out ſuch men that hath, and at this day will curſe God to his face? is not this ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thee there is no other devil but what is in man? for I'le aſſure thee there is ſome this day in <hi>London,</hi> and Country alſo, that in my hearing hath ſaid, God is a devil, and that he hath done that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make good; that God is a tyrant, a Cock and a Bull, a Horſe, and all ſuch like curſed terms; alſo that devil man hath ſaid, <hi>That if God did damn him, he would damn God;</hi> nay, it hath been ſpoken, <hi>That God durſt not damn him, and that God was more beholding to him, then he was to God;</hi> Alſo a man hath ſaid, <hi>That the blood of Chriſt was of no more value then the blood of a dog,</hi> if theſe be not the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> and at the great and terrible day ſhall be rayſed devils, then let them ſay the Lord ſpoke not by me; nay, there is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:92988:23"/> a ſwarm or brood of this curſed ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> that deny a God, or at leaſt they make him a cloak for all their laſcivious luſt, running after the ſteps of their father <hi>Cain</hi> in all manner of wickedneſs: And what is their ſaying, If I can but have my Money-god, let it come right or wrong its all one to me, I will not put it forth to uſury, but I will ſpend it freely upon my luſt; and as for this glorious perſonal God, I own no ſuch God, for what ſay they, Our God is an infinite formleſs ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or an infinite nothing, or an infinite all; that is to ſay, all in beaſts, all in fiſh, all in fowls, all in herbs, trees, and plants, all in men and their wickedneſs too; even thus this curſed ſeed do believe that juſt, holy, glorious God, to be the Author of all their uncleanneſs, ſo that true is that ſaying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. <hi>Thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf;</hi> but at the mighty day of my account, thou ſhalt then have all thy ſins ſet in order before thee, and the ſentence of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed God, paſs upon thee.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:92988:23"/>
                  <p>And whereas thou ſaith, <hi>The devil is a murthering perſecutor of Gods precious ones:</hi> Well, what devil was that, think you, that from the beginning to this day per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the people of God? was it a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil without man or in man? Surely the Scripture with our experience, can to any ſober man make it appear, it was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther devil but man: As inſtance, who perſecuted the Prophets of the Lord of old, was it not the Prieſts and Elders of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Who was it that perſecuted Chriſt Jeſus? was it not their children the holy devout Jews, that murthered the Lord of glory? Who perſecuted the Apoſtles? was it not the ſame generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the curſed ſeed of <hi>Cain?</hi> Who put the Martyrs to the fire? was it a devil without a form, or was it not a devil in Queen <hi>Marys</hi> form? Who is it now that perſecutes the ſubſtantial light or life of the ſeed of faith? is it not the devil in man, or man-devil? Nay had it not been for the late Lord Protector, whoſe ſoul was merciful to tender conſciences: O
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:92988:24"/> had it not been that God had honored him before and above all, in wiſdom to go in and out before Parliaments, and the Prieſts of this Nation; what a bloody perſecuting day had here been in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> and yet you cry out of the devil for a perſecutor, when it is the devil in you; ſo that you ſee there is no other devil but what is that curſed ſeed of <hi>Cain.</hi> O therefore look about you, for the devil that you fear, is in you.</p>
                  <p>Now to the laſt and greateſt appeal the ſeed of <hi>Can</hi> can make for himſelf, is this, <hi>If there be no other Devil but what is in man or woman, then Kings may be devils, Magiſtrates devils, Lawyers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, Merchants devils, Soldiers devils, Doctors devils, and Preachers devils, and ſo at the day of judgement, few other but devils ſhall ariſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> What a Catalogue of great men is here recorded, thou ſuppoſing ſuch men as theſe, its pity to damn them, or at leaſt God will have more mercy on them, then on the poor ragged ſeed of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:92988:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Cain</hi> [and that becauſe] of their greatnes: Surely, if poſſible, thou wouldſt turn God from being God, and that becauſe he ſaith, <hi>He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy: And with our God there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons;</hi> So that mark what is ſaid, What is a King? what is a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate? what is a Doctor? what is a Lawyer? what is a Soldier? what is a Merchant? what is a Preacher? though their houſes be full of gold and ſilver, and their body richly clad with Jewels and raiment? What is all this to the Judge of Juſtice? its but as filthy raggs, no nor the perſons of ſuch men are no more eſteemed then the dunghil begger; Nay, what doth the Lord ſay, <hi>Not many wiſe, not many mighty, not many noble men ſhall be ſaved,</hi> but the poor perſecuted for his names ſake, are his beloved: Again, he ſaith, <hi>It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heaven:</hi> Do you hear, will ye believe, or underſtand that theſe ſayings needs no interpretation, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:92988:25"/> you may ſlight it, take notice that what I now ſay, you ſhall finde it, that ſince God became fleſh, there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in Scripture to thoſe that truly knows him, and ſo profeſſeth him, ſhall be rich in this world; As find me out ten among ten thouſand, from the firſt of <hi>Matthew,</hi> to the laſt of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that were true believers, ſo living and ſo dying; I ſay thou canſt not find out half that number that were really of the ſeed of faith, and rich in this would, ſo few they were then, and ſo few now, that I think it ſhould make the rich of this world to tremble, for though you can paſs the Scripture, with ſome evations of your own, and defer the application of them as concerning your ſelves, yet from my Seed-ſpring, this you ſhall know, that thoſe ſayings, <hi>It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enjoy in his own ſoul the eternal truth,</hi> there being ſuch antipathy betwixt them, that they accord like two contrary elements, <hi>viz.</hi> fire and water, no ſociety
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:92988:25"/> till one hath conquered the other: As in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the riches and glory of this world, it elevates the ſoul beyond its bounds, it finds ſo much content here, that that truth that will not maintain this periſhing fleſhly glory, with all its luſt and pride; Oh it is as hard a ſaying as that of Chriſt to the young man in the Goſpel, when truth preſents it ſelf to a rich worldly man, and yet this man a great profeſſor of the letter, and makes a great flutter in vain repetition to a God thou knows not; yet I ſay, when the eternal truth tenders it ſelf to thy ſoul, in a poor perſecuted diſtreſſed condition, and tells thee I the Lord of glory had not a bed to lay my head on; and thoſe that will raign with me in that endles glory to come, muſt forſake all, &amp; take me for their pattern; and as for the riches here, make as good ſhift as thou canſt, provided thou doth as thou would be done to. Oh ſaith the rich ſoul, This is a hard ſaying indeed, for let me be of what Art or Calling ſoever, if in that Art or Calling I do righteous things, I ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:92988:26"/> be poor enough in this world, for I finde in my Art and Trading, that all men that grows rich, hath got it by cheat and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving thoſe they have to deal with; for if a man deal juſtly, he ſhall have much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do to maintain his family; therefore well might the God of all knowledge ſay, <hi>Not many rich, not many noble, but the poor ſhall enter in at the ſtraight gate;</hi> for the way, the path, the gate, to the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the real durable truth is ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that the ſoul with its body muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in pure and undefiled, not laden with cheats and deceits, as thouſands at this day ſtrives to enter in, and are not able for want of their certificate, that golden Rule, <hi>In doing to others as thou would others ſhould do to thee:</hi> Now if thou ſay, <hi>Where is that man, or how is it poſsible for any man to perform this?</hi> I anſwer, I can both ſhow thee the man and affirm it is poſſible, for ſince I have known the true God, and been made obedient to the rule thereof, mark what I ſay, I have not to my knowledge, done that to another,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:92988:26"/> which I would not the ſame party ſhould do to me; and for the poſſibility thereof, it lieth in thy power to do, minde what I ſay, It is as poſſible for thee to do juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as unjuſtly: As inſtance, thou having a friend that repoſeth confidence in thee, and declareth the truth of his buſineſs unto thee, concerning which he entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thee to do for him, as if occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, thou would have him do the like for thee; now the occaſion upon which thou art imployed, is a buſineſs of great advantage, as a bargain of Land, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize or otherways, which if thou deal with him as for thy ſelf, ſufficient benefit will acrue thereby; but now in the managing of this his affairs, thou findſt thou canſt gain for thy ſelf twenty pound more or leſs, and yet thy friend ſhall accompliſh his deſire, cheaper then if he had aggitated the buſineſs himſelf; and as touching this thy pretended plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing, and ſeeming honeſty, thou haſt contrived a way that he ſhall never know of it, but account himſelf as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:92988:27"/> to thee for this thy great kindneſs and juſt dealing with him, as if it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo. Now ſpeak for thy ſelf, was it not in thy power to give him all or no, and deal plainly? was this any kindeneſs or juſt dealing in the leaſt? or hath it any relation to that Golden ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 12. <hi>Therefore all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them, for this the Law and the Prophets:</hi> No, no, thou wouldſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver imploy him more, but judge him, and ſo look upon him as the ungratefulleſt man living upon the earth; therefore look to thy own ſoul, how it ſtands related to that golden rule aforeſaid, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou finds in thy ſelf a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge towards him, or if ever occaſion of ſuch an account be tendered to thee, thou wilt ſerve him the like; I ſay be thou what thou wilt, thou maiſt ſhake hands like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in cheat and deceit; as thou may call to minde one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable curſed rule betwixt buyer and ſeller, as thus, Suppoſe thou be the ſeller,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:92988:27"/> and I the buyer, I come for ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity which thou haſt, I ask thee the price that thou canſt afford it to live by, thou doth proteſt, as thou intends to be ſaved, it coſt thee ſo much, I having no experience, and believing thee, gives thee thy price, when thou knows, thou haſt cheated me both in the goodneſs of the Commodity, and the price; now judge thou if this be as thou would have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerve thee? or doſt thou think for all thy long prayers and heaven-like car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, that theſe ill gotten riches, by which thou art grown great on the earth, that ſuch as thou ſhalt enter the ſtraight gate, or that thou ſhalt riſe a rich, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous-Saint at the day of judgement? then I may ſay in vain was it for me, to forſake a hundredth pound a year, and expoſe my ſelf and children to ſtrayts, becauſe I couldnot cheat; for I tell thee, if to do juſt and unjuſt be all one, then I ſay with <hi>Paul, Of all men we are moſt miſerable,</hi> when we might be rich, to live poor here, and be damned hereafter. Oh no, no, as ſure
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:92988:28"/> as God is God, thou ſhalt know, that ſo continuing and ſo dying as a cheat, ſhall have all thy heaven here, and everlaſting torment hereafter; therefore wonder not why it is a hard thing for Kings or great men to be ſaved, but rather wonder that any is ſaved: As take account from <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to the coming of Chriſt, and obſerve ſeriouſly how many of them ſhall ariſe Saints; alſo take notice from Chriſt, to the raign of the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, thou ſhalt find it is a hard thing to deal juſtly and be rich in this world; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, from experience I find it ſo far different, yea, ſo contradictory, that from the ſeed of Faith I ſpeak it, to deal juſtly thou cannot be rich, but poor in this world, and yet what ſtriving here is to be rich, yea wiſe and great in this peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing world, not in the leaſt laying to heart that ſaying of <hi>James</hi> 5. 1. <hi>&amp;c. Go to now ye rich men, weep and howl for your miſeries that ſhall come upon you; your riches are corrupted, and your garments moth-eaten; your gold and ſilver is can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered,</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:92988:28"/> 
                     <hi>and the ruſt of them ſhall be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt you, and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were fire; ye have heaped treaſure toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the laſt dayes; ye have lived in pleaſure on the earth and been wanton, ye have nouriſhed your hearts as in a day of ſlaughter, ye have condemned and killed the juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now look about you the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> and tell me to whom was this ſpoken, or whom doth this concern, if not the great men of the earth, or rich men of this world; and yet how few of you do conſider that deſtruction will be the end of this thy fleſhly periſhing glory? Alas, what though thou live thirty, fourty, fifty, or eighty years, this know, thy glaſs is a running, thy brave time will have an end, and to thy bed of ſickneſs thou muſt be brought, when then all thy rich robes and precious Jewels may hange by thee, but thou canſt not make uſe of them, and in room of them death prepares a garment for thee. O then, even then, is a believers joy, which now is thy ſorrow; for in ſtead
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:92988:29"/> of ſpeaking peace to thee, they will be a witneſs againſt thee, yea, a declaration of dreadful things concerning thee, remind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee of all thy proud thoughts and lofty looks; as alſo how thou haſt ſpent thy time in pleaſure on this earth, and been wanton in the day of judgement; yea, cruel in the day of mercy in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, yea, killing the Juſt, that bleſſed ſeed of Faith; now if theſe men ſhall be ſaved, and if thoſe works ſhall be juſtified, that is recorded in <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>viz.</hi> abhorring judgement, perverting all equity, judging for reward, teaching for hire, divining for mony, grinding the faces of the poor, enriching themſelves in the ruine of others; I ſay, if ſuch great men as theſe, that have here enjoyed all the pleaſure and glory of this periſhing world, ſhall enjoy that immortal raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory in the world to come, then minde what will follow, then in vain were the Scriptures written, and to no purpoſe was thoſe great ſufferings of our Lord Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 29.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:92988:29"/> 
                     <hi>And every one that hath forſaken houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life;</hi> and then in the ſame Chapter, Chriſt ſhews from the young mans going away ſorrowful, <hi>How hard a thing it is for a rich man to enter,</hi> yea, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>A rich man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of glory:</hi> and in <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold we have forſaken all and followed thee, what ſhall we have therefore?</hi> now you may read his anſwer was this, <hi>That ye which have followed me in the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Son of man ſhall ſit in the throne of his glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now in all theſe words, expound, or interpret which way ye can to ſtile your fears of death, and your dreadful portion at the great day, I ſay from the Lord of glory you cannot find any colour or tittle in the leaſt that doth encourage or give any admittance to a worldly minded rich
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:92988:30"/> man, for if you minde what you read, you ſhall find all the promiſes here, or in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture elſewhere, doth onely appertain to ſuch that hath forſaken all falſe worſhips and falſe Chriſts, and hath renounced all unjuſt ways or means whereby he hath enriched himſelf, yea he that hath ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a good name with the credit of this world, and is not onely ready to perſecute, but be perſecuted for that glorious, yet deſpiſed man Jeſus; I ſay from the ſpirit of Faith, all the promiſes of the Lord in Scripture doth onely belong to theſe poor deſpiſed ſcum of the earth, as in theſe words, Thou <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or ye my diſciples, or any other of my precious ones, that hath loſt all for me, you are thoſe that ſhall have all gain by me, you ſhall have everlaſting life, and be with me in my Kingdom, yea in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like my ſelf, as mind that ſaying of <hi>James</hi> the ſecond chapter and fifth verſe, <hi>Hearken my beloved brethren, hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od choſen the poor of this world rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, which he</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:92988:30"/> 
                     <hi>hath promiſed to them that love him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now what can be ſaid more, or what more wouldeſt thou have God do for thee? wouldſt thou have him unjuſt, or contradict his own word? then be content with thy rich glory here, and let us have our glory with our God; we grudge not at thy greatneſs in this world, no nor thou ſhalt not hinder us, or detain us from our portion of glory to come, thine is almoſt at an end, ours is yet to come; and ſhall never end; therefore be not deceived, thou canſt not live the life of the devil here, and live eternally with the Lord hereafter: then, as I ſaid before, ſo againſt men and angels I ſhould ſay again, that ſuch as I had better never been born to deprive my ſelf of ſuch a livelihood, as I might not have been inferior to many, and all to live upright and juſtly in this my ſtrange country, which now I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all; Surely, if it were ſo as ſome of <hi>Cains</hi> curſed brood doth ſay, and binde it with an oath, That all ſhall be ſaved, then poor <hi>Paul,</hi> and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:92988:31"/> poor Prophets, and we in theſe days, have made a ſad exchange, but as ſure as God is God, whoſoever thou art, be thou Ranter or Quaker, King or Beggar, thou ſhalt finde at the day of our Saviours ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, that thou ſo dying, ſhalt never be ſaved; and then if it were poſſible, thou wouldſt ſay what I here write, is truth, and ſuch as thou art found lyers.</p>
                  <p>Now one word more to this laſt plea of the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſo as touching this point I have done, which is this: If there be no other devil but what is in man or woman, then thou ſayeſt, Kings may riſe devils, Magiſtrates devils, Lawyers devils, Soldiers devils, Merchants devils, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors devils, yea and Preachers devils, theſe being for the moſt part the richeſt men of this world; and the Scripture in many places extending its language only againſt ſuch men, may cauſe not onely a ſuppoſition in the ſeed of faith, to judge according to the tenor of the inſpired Writ, but alſo a terror upon the ſouls of rich men, in that Chriſt compareth riches
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:92988:31"/> to bryers and thorns, as in that parable of the ſower, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 22. where he ſaith, <hi>And the cares of this world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of riches choak the word, and it becometh unfruitful,</hi> riches being ſuch a ſnare and deceiver of the ſoul, may juſtly, and that not without ſuſpition, cauſe a ſerious examination, whether riches be not the onely inſtrument, why or wherefore the true God nor his word doth not take root within thee: where there is ſo much fulneſs of the treaſure of this world, there can be no admittance for the treaſure of God, ye cannot ſerve two maſters, and that becauſe the riches of this world is in antipathy to the riches of heaven, in that one is periſhing, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther everlaſting, the one clouds or draws the ſoul from God, the other expells miſts, and draws the ſoul to God; ſo that Chriſt knowing it was the greateſt tryal and ſnare to the ſoul, doth declare it a hard thing to enter, yea ſo difficult, that ſince he took upon him the form of fleſh, there hath not, nor now is, not one of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:92988:32"/> knowing the true God, that ſhall be much troubled with the riches of this world; for where riches is, there muſt be a mighty power of faith keeping the ſoul in obedience to its God, and that becauſe where there is riches, it requires the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whole attendance, to give all care and diligence that poſſible may be, to augment it, or at leaſt to uphold the ſtock or principle, in ſo much that it makes him uncapable to caſt his whole care upon the God of endleſs riches. Now to conclude, there is one thing more of great concernment to be ſeriouſly laid to heart by theſe rich men, which is this.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, How thou cameſt to this thy greatneſs, whether it was by birthright, or inheritance, as the eldeſt ſon.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Whether it came by thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſubtile wit and ripe ingenuity, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving thy Art or Calling, by which thou wert capable of, by which fleſhly wiſdom of thine thou art poſſeſt in thy riches?</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:92988:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> from my ſeed-ſpring give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſult of my thoughts as touch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ee, and as ſure as God is God, thou ſhalt finde what I write is truth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For the firſt, Suppoſe in my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I am, kindered or friend, ſhould unexpected by me, give me a thouſand pound a year more or leſs, now it is juſt in me to receive it, and poſſibly as juſtly I improve it, onely here conſiſts the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that if by theſe riches my ſoul is drawn from God, and more delighted in the pleaſure of my riches then God, ſo that I think my ſelf a great man, and now am grown lofty, hard-hearted, and ſuch like corruption attends me, in ſo much that not onely my ſelf, but likewiſe my neighbors, takes notice that I am not like the man I was before.</p>
                  <p>So that now thou that hath thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſucceſſively, is not by Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, provided it prove not a ſnare or a thorn to choak thy ſoul, by having ſuch a deep impreſſion in thy heart, that the infallible truth cannot take root in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:92988:33"/> thee, onely here is the haz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>id, if thou uſe it as though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>not, which is no eaſie thing, yet if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> canſt make uſe of it to the glory of our God, by feeding the hungry, and clothing the naked in the name of a Prophet or a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, ſo ſaid, and ſo done, thou ſhalt have a Prophets or righteous mans reward, which is eternal life in the world to come; I ſay if theſe things, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of thy riches, are performed by them, then it may be thou art one of thoſe few of the rich and noble that ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thou that haſt got thy riches by thy ſubtile wit, is much different from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that the firſt was freely given, ſo that he came juſtly by it; but as for thee, thou beſt knows how thou cameſt to thy greatneſs; for thou haſt heard, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, it is a wonder for a man to do juſt and upright things, and yet grow rich; therefore the Scripture calls thee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and that the more thou mayeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not many years ago thou waſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:92988:33"/> but a poor Journy-man of thy Trade, not worth a groat, but in debt, and now in theſe few years thou art worth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</p>
                  <p>O friend, deal plainly with thy ſoul, though thou may hide it from man, thou canſt not hide it from God, for thy ways are naked to his glorious piercing eye, that although thou may blind man with thy fair carriage and ſugared pretences, ſeemingly gilt over with holineſs and purity of life, yet for all this our glorious perſonal God doth know, and in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will read, how many thou haſt cheated and murthered to make thy ſelf great by undoing of others: In this thing are not moſt of your Doctors over ſhoes and boots in this crying ſin, in taking a crown for that which coſt but ſix pence, and not onely ſo, but for want of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mercy, deſtroys the poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to the utter ruin of his family, ſo that thou art of that number that tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the broad way, that at laſt will lead thee to the deſtruction of thy ſoul eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:92988:34"/> yea world without end; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take notice, that God is not afraid to call thee to account, or that he will be more merciful to thee then a beggar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy greatneſs, or that thy white hand or fair face adorned with Silk, Gold or Silver, ſhall cauſe an eye of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion more to thee becauſe of that, then to a black deformed creature; No, no, our God thou ſhalt finde, ſeeth not as man ſeeth, neither is his thoughts as mans, if he were, then had the fair, neat, rich, proud daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> been reſpected, but in ſtead of a bleſſing, he blaſted all their glory and their bravery, as you may read at large, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3. from the 16 to the end, firſt repeating how they walked with ſtretched-out necks and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as you go, and making a tinkling with your feet, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in ſtead of ſhewing mercy, did ſmit with a ſcab the crowns of the heads of the daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi> yea, the Lord did diſcover their ſecret parts, and took away all their bravery of tinkling or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:92988:34"/> about their feet, their cauls and round tires like the Moon, the chains, bracelets &amp; mufflers, the bonnets, tablets, ear-rings, and noſe-jewels, wimples, and criſping pins, the glaſſes and fine linen, the vails, with the changeable ſuits of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</p>
                  <p>O if God were a reſpecter of perſons, here was invitations plenty: but you may read, <hi>that in ſtead of a ſweet ſmell, he gave them a ſtink; and in ſtead of a girdle, a rent, in ſtead of well-ſet hair, baldneſs: in ſtead of beauty, burning;</hi> yea, and that with eternal burnings, ſhall all proud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of this infallible truth undergo, at the great and terrible day of our Saviors appearance; concerning which I ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen at large in the laſt Chapter. Thus much in anſwer to your Pleas, now I ſhall prove from Scripture the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> to be of the devil.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:92988:35"/>
                  <head>The devil or Seed of <hi>Cain</hi> infallibly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from experience in Scripture.</head>
                  <p>II. BEcauſe of the great oppoſition that may ariſe up againſt this glorious Truth, through the exceeding pride and unbelief in the hearts of moſt men, give me leave to cite a few Scriptures in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this work in hand: In the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> the third Chapter, you ſhall find it thus written, <hi>Not as</hi> Cain <hi>which was of that wicked one, and ſlew his brother:</hi> Alſo in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> it is thus written, <hi>He that ſoweth the good ſeed is the Son of man, and the field is the world; the good ſeed are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the kingdom, and the tares are the children of the wicked one, and the enemy that ſoweth them is the devil.</hi> Moreover, in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter of S. <hi>John,</hi> Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the God of Truth ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Ye are of your father the devil, and the luſts of your father ye will do: he hath been a murtherer from the beginning, and abode</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:92988:35"/> 
                     <hi>not in the truth, becauſe there was no truth in him; when he ſpeaketh a lie, then he ſpeaketh of his own, for he is a liar, and the father thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My ſpiritual and rational friends which are ſober, was not <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lying man that ever was born of a woman, ſeeing no true Chriſtian can gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it? was not that curſed <hi>Cain</hi> from the beginning, that murthering devil and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lies, ſpoken of by Chriſt afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, in anſwer to thoſe carnal Jews which boaſted themſelves to be of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed? and were not thoſe luſtful murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-minded Jews or Gentiles which our Lord branded with titles of ſerpents, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, children of the devil, and ſuch like filthy Canaanites, which proceeded out of the ſpirit of curſed <hi>Cain</hi> that old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, dragon-devil, and father of all the damned in this world, and not from the ſpirit of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though they might proceed from his loins according to the fleſh, through mixtures of ſeeds in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages: <hi>the ſons of God ſaw the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:92988:36"/> 
                     <hi>of men to be fair, and they took of them to be their wives.</hi> Again, though the bleſſed Iſraelites and curſed Canaan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites are mixed together by carnal copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſince the prince of devils became fleſh, yet you that are ſpiritual may know, that the Lord Ieſus that made them both, knew how to ſeparate them for all their cloſe union, and to call them by names anſwerable to their own natures.</p>
                  <p>As conſider, did not the glorious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and bleſſed Redeemer himſelf, make a clear diſtinction between two worlds or generations, when he ſaid, <hi>I pray not for the world, but for them that thou haſt given me out of the world;</hi> can you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that are ſober, imagine or think, that there is any ſpiritual ſalvation for theſe men or women, which the Saviour of the world excludes in his petition: Moreover, it is wtitten, that the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>We know that we are of God, and the whole world lyeth in wickedneſs:</hi> Behold, ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones of the moſt high God, is it not as clear as the light it ſelf, that there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:92988:36"/> is two diſtinct whole worlds, according to that ſaying, <hi>Then all Iſrael ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> a redeemed world of elect Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, and an unredeemed world of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Canaanites, that were never truly loſt in themſelves, and therefore never capable of being found in Chriſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> where it is thus written, <hi>For there are certain men crept in, which were of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men, which turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, and denying Chriſt the onely Lord, wo unto them, for they have followed the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and are caſt away by the deceit of</hi> Balaams <hi>wages, and periſh in the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying of</hi> Core: Thus is it not clear unto all ſuch that have in them any faith in the truth of the Scripture, that there is two diſtinct whole worlds, to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the divine glory of Election, and everlaſting ſhame of Rejection? a curſed <hi>Cain,</hi> a bleſſed <hi>Abel;</hi> a ſubtile ſerpent, and a ſimple Saint; a ſcoffing carnal <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> and a ſpiritual <hi>Iſaac;</hi> a bloody min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:92988:37"/> 
                     <hi>Eſau,</hi> and a merciful minded <hi>Jacob;</hi> a perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> and a prophetical <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> a treacherous <hi>Judas,</hi> and a gracious and glorious <hi>Jeſus,</hi> from the beginning of the world unto the end thereof; yea, and a bleſſed <hi>Seth</hi> born in the ſtead of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> to bring forth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the juſt, that the Lord of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory, might according to the fleſh, as well as the ſpirit, ſpring from a ſpiritual line of his own light of life eternal, and not from a rational or carnal line of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death in chains of utter darkneſs; which if it had power, according to its curſed deſire, it would deſtroy God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect men and angels, heaven and earth, and all in them, and it ſelf alſo, rather then be ſubject to any, or might not onely it ſelf bear rule over all.</p>
                  <p>But now to the matter in hand, and withal conſider what you read, for it high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns you to look about you, that if there ſhould be any evil angels, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils living in the air, and a devil amongſt them, called <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the prince of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:92988:37"/> then I ſay, what need any man trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf with the leaſt fear of eternal death, what wickedneſs ſoever is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thee; why? becauſe if a man is tempted by any devil but what is in his own nature onely, that evil ſpirit is to be eternally damned, and the man ſet free; nay moreover, if ſin or evil iſſued not from mans unclean reaſon or lying ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination within him, is it poſſible, think you, that any man ſhould be tormented, as ſome men are, with an inward burning through a ſecret fear of eternal ſufferings riſing in them, from the guilt of former evils committed againſt the light of their own conſciences; furthermore, ſeeing all men which live after the fleſh, muſt die or periſh, and that mans own luſt is that imaginary devil from whence proceeds all ſin or evil.</p>
                  <p>Without controverſie though men or angels ſhould gainſay it, there are no other evil ſpirits, angels, or devils, but unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful men and women onely: Again, if envy, pride, covetouſneſs hypocriſie, luſt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:92988:38"/> and ſuch like, be the devil in man, then are not men and women thoſe devils that are under the power of thoſe evils? I would fain know from the learned men of this world, whether there are any other evil angels or devils beſides mankinde, that luſt after women, or ſilver, or honor, or revenge, or any kinde of evil whatſoever? truly if thoſe ſuppoſed wiſe men that talk ſo much of the ſublilty of the prince of the air, that rules in the children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, could poſſibly know that their own imaginary Reaſon was that evill ſpirit or prince of all their airy diſputes concerning God, angels, devils, Heaven, hell, eternal glory or ſhame to come, which they know not of according to truth, then in ſtead of their reioycing in the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many men in relation unto their natural gifts, their own ſpirits would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately become the principle of all thoſe howling, groaning ſerpent-devils ſpoken of in Holy Writ, even in the ſight of elect men and angels in this mortal life.</p>
                  <p>Again, is it not againſt all ſpiritual or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:92988:38"/> rational ſenſe, that any man, angel or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſhould ſuffer eternal damnation for the ſin of another, or for anothers tempting him to ſin or evil? Moreover, doth it ſtand to very good ſenſe, that, yea that creature that is left to himſelf to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted unto ſin or evil, and overcome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and remains under the power of it to their lives end? its requiſite at the great day he ſhould ſuffer for his own ſin, and not for anothers iniquity: wherefore, judge you, is it not one of the vaineſt things in the world, for any man to think that there is any other evil ſpirit, angel, or devil that tempts him to any motion, imagination, thought, deſire, word, or action of rebellion againſt God or man, but the proud, lying, envious devil living in his whole man, as aforeſaid?</p>
                  <p>Therefore let no man that profeſſeth ſpiritual light or life in him, for very ſhame ſay, that God can be tempted, or tempt any man unto ſin or evil, neither let him ſay, that any evil ſpirit, angel, or devil in the air, or earth, or in the water,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:92988:39"/> or in the fire, tempts him to commit any ſin or evil, but that airy, watery, fiery, luſtful, fleſhly devil dwelling in his own body; I ſay, let him know [that, yea, that] is the prince of the air, which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the abſenting vertue of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, begets thoſe legions of devils, or luſts in the ſoul of man; and it is the true light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in all his new born babes, that cruſheth the Cockatrice eggs before they become ſerpent-devils, to ſting the whole man with fear of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death.</p>
                  <p>So that, underſtand what I ſay, thoſe devils which by the powerful word of the Lord Jeſus were caſt out of <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene,</hi> or any other creature ſpoken of in Holy Writ, were onely all maner of filthy diſeaſes, or violent fiery diſtempers in man, that hurried him about any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate wickedneſs whatſoever, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times increaſing ſo powerfully, as you may read in <hi>Mark</hi> the fifth, that it did not onely occaſion him to rend his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and break iron chains, but alſo he is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:92988:39"/> ready to tear any one in pieces, until the Lord of Glory ſhined into his diſtemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoul, with that golden Grace of true Faith, through which that imaginary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is chained up, whereby all his fleſhly goods were ſpoiled of ever having power in him as formerly, and being now in his right minde at the glorious feet of Chriſt Jeſus, through his own pure light, leading him into heavenly raptures, in reference unto his eternal glory, at his viſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the clouds with all his mighty Angels.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſeriouſly conſider, that if <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Abel</hi> were both begotten by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> upon the body of <hi>Eve,</hi> as for the moſt part all men vainly imagine, from one bare Scripture-record which they underſtand not, I would know of that man that is offended with me concerning this point, why <hi>Cain</hi> was nominated in Holy Writ to be of that wicked one aforeſaid, and branded as an out-caſt, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive, vagabond, and curſed from the divine preſence of the Creator, and caſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:92988:40"/> out of the natural preſence of his parents for ever, and condemned with <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Core</hi> as a periſhing caſt-away? This I am ſure of, that no ſpiritual rational man that is ſober, dare ſay that either <hi>Adam</hi> or <hi>Eve</hi> was that wicked one from whence the curſed ſpirit of <hi>Cain</hi> ſprang, why? becauſe there is no ſuch opprobrious names attributed unto them through the ſacred Scriptures; Moreover, you may know that, yea that wicked one from whence <hi>Cains</hi> ſpirit proceeded, could not poſſibly have any relation to <hi>Adam</hi> or <hi>Eve,</hi> though <hi>Cain</hi> was conceived in her womb, and born of her body, and that becauſe there was an abſolute curſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced upon the Angelical Serpent and his ſeed in her womb, as aforeſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any after-promiſe in Holy Writ, for ever being redeemed by the Creator; but on the contrary, you know there was a gracious promiſe by the Creator himſelf of the Redemption of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their fallen eſtate, with their whole generation of righteous <hi>Abels, Seths,</hi> or
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:92988:40"/> 
                     <hi>Abrahams,</hi> in that glorious hidden ſaying, <hi>The Seed of the woman ſhall break the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now one Scripture more, which ſhall be againſt all gainſayers interpreted, which is this, <hi>Matthew</hi> the fourth, beginning at the firſt verſe: <hi>Then was Jeſus led up of the ſpirit into the wilderneſs to be tempted of the devil, and when he had faſted for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days and forty nights, he was afterward an hungred; and when the tempter came to him, he ſaid, If thou be the Son of God, command that theſe ſtones be made bread: then he anſwered, Man ſhall not live by bread onely, but by every word of God, or that word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God: then the devil taketh him up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy City, and ſetteth him on a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the temple, and ſaith unto him, If thou be the Son of God, caſt thy ſelf down, for it is written, He hath given his angels charge concerning thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Again, the devil taketh him up into an exceeding high mountain, and ſheweth him all the kingdoms of the world, and the</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:92988:41"/> 
                     <hi>glory thereof, and ſaith unto him, All theſe things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In that theſe hidden ſayings hath their dependence on the precedent Chapter, I muſt from thence make way to this divine Secret: As if thou couldſt but underſtand what thou readeſt, thou ſhalt finde, that as ſoon as ever Chriſt was baptized by <hi>John,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt fell upon him, that did impower him to encounter with the devil; in which Diſpute we muſt obſerve theſe two particulars.
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Who this tempter or devil was.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>The nature of this temptation.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, take notice that this tempter was one of the wiſeſt and ſobereſt, yet ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Diſputant amongſt the Phariſees and Sadduces, and therefore appointed by them to have conference with Chriſt, as by and by you ſhall read; for if you caſt your eyes on <hi>John</hi> the third, the fifth, ſixth and ſeventh verſes you ſhall finde, <hi>there went out to him</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and all</hi> Judea, <hi>and all the region round about</hi> Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:92988:41"/> 
                     <hi>and were baptized of him in</hi> Jordan, <hi>confefsing their ſins;</hi> as touching theſe <hi>John</hi> uſed no words of reproof or diſlike in the leaſt, but when he ſaw many of the Phariſees and Sadduces come to his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, he forthwith upbraided them with a ſad, yet juſt ſentence, ſaying, <hi>O genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vipers, who hath forewarned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi> &amp;c. as if he ſhould have ſaid, Ye are the children of that wicked one, that onely comes to diſpute and to cavel, therefore <hi>John</hi> cuts them ſhort with theſe words, <hi>Bring forth fruits meet for repentance, and think not to ſay within your ſelves, we have</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>to our father:</hi> Then <hi>John</hi> proceeds further, and tells them, <hi>I indeed baptize you with water unto repentance, but he that cometh after me, is mightier then I, whoſe ſhoes I am not worthy to bare, he ſhall bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize you with the holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now when the Phariſees and Sadduces heard this, they forthwith commiſsiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one of the wiſeſt and ſubtileſt devil amongſt them, which by experience they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:92988:42"/> found was beſt verſed in Scripture, to ſee if this man-devil could perſwade the Lord Jeſus to baptize them with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire: Now that you may no longer doubt, but that this tempter or devil was onely a man, as aforeſaid, caſt thy eye into <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 6. and the ſixth verſe, where it is thus written, <hi>Ye ſhall not tempt the Lord your God as ye tempted him in Maſſah,</hi> ſo read <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 9. Now tell me friend, who thoſe were that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted the Lord, were they not the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> men and women? So this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter or devil that I am now treating of, was onely a wiſe ſubtile man, as you have already heard, and will in this temptation be made more apparent.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To the nature of the temptation, beginning at theſe words: <hi>Then was Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus led up of the Spirit into the wilderneſs to be tempted of the devil.</hi> Firſt minde, the Spirit that led Ieſus up into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, was the Holy Ghoſt which came upon him at the baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> a little before the tempter came, as you may
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:92988:42"/> read in the laſt verſe of the third of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew.</hi> I have found it true by experience, that whoſoever hath received the Holy Spirit, cannot be free from the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the devil, that is, the cavelling, contentious diſputes of unreaſonable and unmerciful men: But,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in the next place I ſhall give you to underſtand, that this wilderneſs here ſpoken of, was not a wilderneſs yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fruit for the ſupporting of life, where nothing but wilde beaſts void of reaſon doth inhabit, as the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> doth imagine, and the learned of that ſeed do vainly teach: though this wilderneſs was the ſame that <hi>John</hi> quotes in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 13. ſaying, <hi>The voice of one crying in the wilderneſs, prepare ye the way of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Now let any ſober man judge the black darkneſs that is over the learned, to think that <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould cry the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Lord to a wilderneſs of wood and wilde beaſts, that hath no underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to receive it! and as great a dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is for thee to think that any devil
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:92988:43"/> without man, or devil-man, could ſo far overcome Chriſt, as to lead him into ſuch a wilderneſs, no, no: therefore take notice that wilderneſs <hi>Iohn</hi> preached in, and this wilderneſs Chriſt was lead up into, was onely the wilderneſs of mans heart, whoſe hearts are as barren as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural wilderneſs that beareth no fruit, as unto the true knowledge of things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unto eternal life: O minde what you read, it was the wilderneſs of mans heart, and not ſuch a wilderneſs as <hi>Moſes</hi> led the people of Iſrael through; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did <hi>Iohn</hi> preach, nor was in any ſuch wilderneſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Its ſaid, Chriſt faſted forty days and forty nights, but from what he faſted is not in the leaſt mentioned, therefore I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that as <hi>Moſes</hi> faſted forty days and forty nights in the mount from natural food, ſo did Chriſt faſt forty days and forty nights in the ſpiritual, that is, Chriſt did baptize none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the Holy Ghoſt nor with fire, neither did he do any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle for the ſpace of ſix weeks, and the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:92988:43"/> original of this was, that he might be tempted of the ſubtile ſerpentine devil-man, as aforeſaid, which made that devil-man ſay, <hi>If thou be the Son of God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that theſe ſtones be made bread;</hi> however thou that readeſt mayeſt not apprehend this, yet let me tell thee that man-devil did not mean the hard ſtones that we tread upon, no more then <hi>Iohn</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham.</hi> Oh what abſurdity is it in any man to think that God would of natural dead ſtones, raiſe them up ſpiritual living children, no, no: when the devil-man ſaid, <hi>Command that theſe ſtones be made bread</hi> [which was this] Command this ſtony heart of mine, and the ſtony hard hearts of the Phariſees and Sadduces that ſent me, command them to be made hearts of fleſh, by baptizing of us with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire, whereby I and others may ſo believe, that we may become true bread unto Chriſt; for in <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 32, 34. there ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I have me at to eat that</hi>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:92988:44"/> 
                     <hi>ye know not of,</hi> meaning his diſpute with the woman of <hi>Samaria:</hi> as touching this, it was his meat and drink to do the will of his Father, which will was to baptize his Elect with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire, without which no man could have eternal life abiding in him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Then the devil taketh Jeſus up into the holy City, and ſetteth him on a pinacle of the temple:</hi> Obſerve that the City and pinacle of the Temple, were both in the ſelf ſame place, yet underſtand that the Temple and the City ſignifie one and the ſame thing; as from the words of <hi>Paul, Defile not the temple of God, whoſe temple ye are; yea, ye are the temples of the holy Ghoſt, and the city of the living God,</hi> as is recorded in the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> and yet you ſhall finde, though the Saints are the City and Temple of God, that the Scripture calls the Nation of the Jews the holy City; ſo that I know that was the holy City that the devil man took Chriſt up into, and there in the moſt eminent or higheſt place of the Temple,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:92988:44"/> ſtated his temptation in the pinacle, that is nothing elſe but the high temptation that this devil uſed out of his own high ſpirit of reaſon, ſaying, <hi>Caſt thy ſelf down,</hi> that is, ſubmit unto this people which in <hi>Moſes</hi> time were the onely Nation or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God, do but ſubmit to be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or King, in condeſcending to us, there can no harm befal thee, in that he hath given his angels charge concerning thee, thou being the Son of God and our King, we ſhall conquer the whole world; but Chriſts kingdom not being of this world, he tells them, as at other times, <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God:</hi> It might well be called the high temptation of the devil, that if it had been poſſible to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne Chriſt of his immortal Crown and Kingdom, and crowned him King over a mortal, bloody and periſhing king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, I ſay, as in relation to the ſtrength and ſubtilty of this temptation, a man might well be called devil.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Again the devil taketh him up into an exceeding high mountain, and ſheweth</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:92988:45"/> 
                     <hi>him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory thereof, and ſaith, All theſe will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you could underſtand the Scriptures, you ſhall read it calleth rich wicked men <hi>Mountains,</hi> and poor belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men <hi>Valleys;</hi> as ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi> chap. 40. verſe 4. <hi>Every valley ſhall be exalted, and every mountain ſhall be made low:</hi> there is very little of the New Teſtament to be underſtood in the letter, but ſpirit onely; therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>My words are ſpirit and life,</hi> ſo that if thou couldeſt ſee with an eye of Faith, then thou couldeſt with me acknowledge that this exceeding high mountain which the devil ſhewed Chriſt, and all the kingdoms of the world with the glory of them, were all in the devils own heart; for if you minde the Chief Prieſts and Rulers, from whence this devil-man was ſent, they in their Councel inſtructed him, that if that Chriſt to whom he was ſent, would but come and ſubmit, yea, ſide with them;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:92988:45"/> for ſubmitting you muſt underſtand, is no leſs then to worſhip, that if Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus would but ſubmit to be their king and governor, then they would aſſure him he ſhould have all the kingdoms of the world; for thou being the Son of God, no earthly king can ſtand before thee, for in ſo doing we ſhall have the rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole world, and the glory thereof, which if thou wouldſt but condeſcend to this, we could make our words truth, that <hi>Herod, Pilate</hi> and <hi>Ceſar</hi> would give place to thy crown and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by which we ſhould become a greater people then ever we were: theſe and ſuch like thoughts was in the Prieſts and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, which they thought they had ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compacted together, as a mountain not onely ſtrong and great, but a high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain over-topping all other mountains whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>So that now you have the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Scripture, which till this laſt Witneſs could never be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that the high mountain there ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:92988:46"/> of, was the moderate, wiſe, and high read Conſultations in the breaſts of the Rulers, given into a particular, moderate, wiſe, high, learned man, much read in the Law and the Prophets, to tempt, and if poſſible, to perſwade Chriſt to yield to this his high and learned Poſition; but you may read this man-devils mountain was too weak, and too low, for the high immortal God to reſt or caſt himſelf down upon; for to that end he came not into this kingdom to be King, but to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil his own determined will, in deſtroying him that had the power of death even the devil, yea, that devil-man that would, if poſſible, have deceived God himſelf, and ſo returns his poſitive Anſwer, <hi>Get thee hence, Satan, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r it is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> that is, thou oughteſt to be ruled by me, and not I by thee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore depart, my kingdom is not of this world, but of that world which is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, immortal, and to all eternity. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which that man-devil leaveth him, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:92988:46"/> for not prevailing, and Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed by his Meſſenger from his glorious Kingdom above the ſtars.</p>
                  <p>Queſtion. <hi>If this be infallible what you have here written, then may you ask me, How comes it the Learned of this world could not, as well as this Witneſs, make known this hidden divine Secret, ſeeing they give themſelves wholly to finde out the true interpretation of the Scriptures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> What ever the Learned of this world dream of finding out the inviſible things of Eternity, by ſearching into Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Records, and comparing them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet know this, the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath locked up all the principal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Scriptures in his own ſpiritual breaſt, that he by an immediate inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may diſpoſe of them into the ſpirits of elect men and angels, moſt advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for his own glory, and their conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore minde what you read, and ſeriouſly obſerve, that the Scriptures runs not in the line of Reaſon, but in the line of Faith, Inſpiration, or Revelation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:92988:47"/> to thoſe ſayings in the <hi>Hebrews</hi> and other Records: By Faith the divine Work of Creation, and wonderful My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Redemption was, and is known, with the immortal eternal Glory, and everlaſting ſhame of mens perſons in the end of the world: but of the contrary you ſhall never read in any place of Scripture, that any man in the leaſt knew the things of eternal Glory by any kinde of rational comprehenſion wharſoever; I confeſs the natural Reaſon of man is a very good handmaid, if it be well qualified with the ſpiritual dame of divine Faith, for illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the things of God unto weak com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions; but as for truly underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the inviſible things of God by the higheſt reaſon that ever was in man or angel, it is utterly impoſſible, as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and that becauſe though the ſpirit of reaſon were never ſo pure, yet you may know reaſons nature is but a deſire after the knowledge of the divine nature of that Spirit from whence reaſon had its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving being: but of the contrary, ſpiritual
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:92988:47"/> Truth or Faith, is of the divine nature of God himſelf, and therefore in what ſoul ſoever that Heavenly Seed is ſown, it ſpringeth up in that ſpirit all variety of divine knowledge, with glorious raptures in reference unto life eternal, by vertue of an intercourſe with the eternal Spirit from whence it came. Moreover, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs a man that is indued with a <hi>Solomon-like</hi> gift of natural reaſon, may be able to comprehend all words, whether they are ſpoken in a good form, ſenſe or language, or no; yea, and ſuch a man may be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in diſputes about the glorious things of Eternity; but as for thy real under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whether there were, or be any ſuch eternal things or no, thou haſt no certain knowledge of that at all, but thy bare thoughts onely, which if equally weighed in that balance, it may be true, or it may be falſe, and all this is for want of an infallibility of Truth it ſelf; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though the divine things of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Majeſty be nothing elſe but ſpiritual purity, of an infallible truth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:92988:48"/> yet unto that rational wiſe man, they are nothing but non-ſenſical blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy or lying tales, till his reaſon is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in him by a true and heavenly Faith.</p>
                  <p>Now thou that haſt peruſed this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, if thou underſtandeſt what thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, mayeſt behold how infallibly I have proved both by Reaſon, Faith and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that there is no other devil but what is in man and woman; alſo how this devil came to be a devil; ſo that if thou wilt not, becauſe thou canſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, much good may that imaginary devil do thee, yet by the way let me tell thee one word, which is irrevocable, that thou canſt not now really, nor at thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection ſhalt finde, or in thy ſelf feel any other devil, but thy ſoul onely, which if it were poſſible for thee then to utter thy ſelf, thou wouldeſt tell me what now I write to thee, was the naked truth; but then, even then I ſhall be far enough from thee, in that I ſhall be with the Lord above the Stars; this thou ſhalt finde, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:92988:48"/> this I ſhall be (as ſure as God is God) for believe me whether thou wilt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no, I do not write now as formerly I have done, <hi>viz.</hi> hab nab, as a man onely indued with reaſon, but take notice I write from that revealed Seed-ſpring within me. Now to the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> his Education.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II. The Seed of <hi>Cain</hi> his Education or bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, undeniably proved againſt any of his tribe that ſhall oppoſe it.</head>
               <p>AS touching this I ſhall not need to ſpend much ink or paper, and that becauſe not onely Scripture, but likewiſe experience doth confirm, that there is none of the Seed of Faith ſo honorably educated as the rich ſort of the ſeed of <hi>Cain;</hi> for indeed to whom doth the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and government of this world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to, but to them? and therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that in the bounds of reaſon can be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:92988:49"/> attained unto, but his ſeed enjoys it; nay, they are ſo exactly educated in the affairs of this world, that by their reaſon they are able to comprehend all words whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are ſpoken in a Philoſophical form, ſenſe, or language; nay, many of them are not onely mighty in diſputes as touching the Government of this their kingdom, but they are alſo able in diſpute about the glorious things of Eternity, though they underſtand not the matter diſputed of in the leaſt; for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Neither can they know them becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned;</hi> for their education in the greateſt knowledge is but natural, and therein they are able to dictate unto the unlearned of their ſeed, laws and rules to preſerve this their kingdom in peace among themſelves; for you muſt underſtand what wiſdom Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning can teach them ſhall not be wanting, and the wiſdom they attain unto, is not that ſpiritual or divine Wiſdom, for this onely belongs to the Seed of Faith; As read but 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4, 5, and 6 verſes, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:92988:49"/> there you ſhall hear <hi>Paul</hi> ſhew the vaſt difference of the wiſdom of Faith, from the wiſdom of fleſh; for the wiſdom of <hi>Cain</hi> is a meer cheat, yea, leads him forth to nothing but pride, oppreſſion and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, for by that wiſdom they put the Lord of Life to death, as in the eighth verſe: therefore you that have eyes may ſee what this learning and knowledge is the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> are tutored in, that it is no other but the wiſdom of this world, which is fooliſhneſs with God, and that is the cauſe they come to tempt or diſpute with the Seed of Faith, whoſe wiſdom is given him by inſpiration or revelation, in the demonſtration of the Spirit; I ſay, becauſe the wiſdom of <hi>Cain</hi> cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the things of the Spirit of God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this precious ſoul, O how they rayl with tearms of a fool, an aſs, a dunce, a coxcomb, a heretical blaſphemer, an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus, one that hath no ſenſe; theſe and ſuch like tearms this curſed Brood will brand the Seed of Faith with, the onely wiſe men in Chriſt; for which cauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:92988:50"/> the Lord in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19. ſaith, <hi>I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the wiſdom of the wiſe, and will bring to nothing the underſtanding of the prudent. Where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer of this world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this world?</hi> and all becauſe the fooliſhneſs of God in the Seed of Faith, is wiſer then that great knowledge in the ſeed of <hi>Cain:</hi> for take this infallible truth along with you, which is this, that the Scriptures in the life and power of them were never given to the wiſe learned men in thoſe days; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>to you it is given to know the myſtery,</hi> to you my Diſciples, or elected Seed of Faith, to you, and for your ſakes did I ſpeak this: and therefore it was the wiſe, learned Prieſts and Rulers did impriſon and put to death, not onely the Diſciples, but Chriſt alſo, as Blaſphemers, for publiſhing this Scripture, which now their wiſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do make a Trade of, and will not onely impriſon, but, if poſſible, put to death the onely Witneſſes and true Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:92988:50"/> of this Holy Writ which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by inſpiration, for the proper uſe of his bleſſed Seed of Faith.</p>
               <p>Again, the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> are educated in the fulneſs and plenty of this world, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that there is no novelty, delicate or dainty, that by the ſpirit of reaſon can be invented, but for their belly it is prepared; as alſo no new antick faſhion can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, either of ſilk, gold, or ſilver, but their backs are adorned with it, nay, there is no attendance of men and maid-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that this their kingdom can afford, but the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> enjoys it; yea, they are ſo tenderly and princely brought up at home and abroad, and ſo hurried in their Coaches and Sedans, that if poſſible the cold wind ſhould not blow on them, nor the glorious Sun with his beams ſhould ſcorch them, ſo careful are they of their beauty and comely, ſtreight, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per perſons, that if poſſible, there ſhall not be a wrinckle on their hands, nor a ſpot on their faces, unleſs it be of their own making, for the more grace of their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:92988:51"/> comely perſons; thus what by art in their wiſdom can be invented, ſhall not in the leaſt be wanting, if it can be had for gold or ſilver; and whatever Science, Paſtime or Pleaſure their ſoul can deſire, as Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, Hunting, Bowling, Shooting, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, at Dice, Cards, or Tables, or any other delight of Muſick, Dancing, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Ladies, with the ſatisfaction of their greateſt luſt, and that with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pomp and ſtate this their heaven can afford; and then in the laſt place for carriage and behavior none in this world like unto them, as obſerve how proud, and <hi>Lucifer-like,</hi> their father, they carry their heads, inſomuch that they know not what faſhion or coloured Perriwig to hang upon it: and when they meet any of their brethren, O what congeying and bowing with Cap in hand to the ground, ſaluting each other with theſe and ſuch like complementary tearms, as, <hi>Your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Sir,</hi> or, <hi>Your ſervants ſervant, Sir,</hi> or, <hi>Madam,</hi> and <hi>fair Lady, I am yours to command by night or by day,</hi> and that with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:92988:51"/> ſo much ſtatelineſs and comely behavior, that I wonder thou ſhouldeſt be affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the name or perſon of the devil, conſidering what a glorious, proud, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtical creature the devil is, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But now if you ask me, <hi>Are all the ſeed of</hi> Cain <hi>thus educated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No: for you may underſtand ſome are brought up to one Calling or another, that ſome of them do undergo hard labor and great pains, to maintain themſelves with their families, in this their periſhing kingdom, ſo that they have neither gold nor ſilver [the duſt of this earth] to mannage ſuch a fleſhly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious education, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And others there are that are educated, yea, brought up ſervants, yea ſlaves, to the great Rabbies of their ſeed, which none of them have that attendance, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, delights &amp; pleaſures as aforeſaid; but on the contrary, are deprived of all that their happineſs the other enjoy, inſomuch that in ſtead of giving relief, they beg re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; in ſtead of a Bed of Doun, they lye
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:92988:52"/> on a bed of ſtraw; in ſtead of being clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with ſilk, they are clad with rags, yea many times ready to ſtarve for want of food; ſo that you may behold there is not onely rich, but poor, miſerable, ragged devils, that ſhall riſe at the day of our eternal Gods appearance, ſo that I ſay theſe of all the tribe or generation, are to be pitied, if pity did belong to them, to conſider what affliction they undergo in this their heaven, and yet be eternally damned hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi> But now you may ſay unto me, and that ſeemingly affirm, both from my writing and the Scripture, in that I have before treated much of the rich men of this world, how hard a thing it is for them to walk in the ways of God, they being ſo educated in the pomp and glory of this world; which I ſay, and your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience findes it is the greateſt thief that ſteals away the heart of man, and ſo makes that ſoul as difficult, as a woman in travail, to enter into the life and power of the Goſpel; therefore we being poor,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:92988:52"/> and the Scripture ſaith, the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eives the Goſpel, we much marvel how your writing will be found truth in Scripture, that any poor ſhould riſe devils, when the Scripture ſaith, it is onely the poor that receives the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> From this thy curious Query I ſhall anſwer thee in thoſe words of <hi>James</hi> 2. 5. where it is thus written, <hi>Hearken my beloved brethren, hath not God choſen the poor of this world, rich in Faith, and heirs of the kingdom which he hath promiſed to them that love him?</hi> Now if you intend theſe poor, I affirm what you ſay, yea, from my Seed-ſpring I declare, not one of theſe poor ſhall riſe devils, in that theſe are the Seed of Faith, and educated in the knowledge of eternal Truth, yea, tutored by the ſpirit of divine Wiſdom: But now tell me how many of theſe poor you can finde among the poor ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> for if thou underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt what thou readeſt, thou ſhalt finde, though the Seed of Faith for the moſt part are but poor in this world, <hi>viz.</hi> your
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:92988:53"/> kingdom, yet minde what the Holy Writ ſaith, though poor in eſtate, yet they are rich in faith, ſo that theſe poor by Faith receives the Goſpel; therefore take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this, it is not poverty in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man that makes thee rich in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man; for if you could diſcern, by the ſpirit of Faith you ſhall finde, that the major part of the poor in this world, are as poor in faith, yea ſo poor, that they cannot give thee the leaſt account what God is, or what a rich treaſure it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in God, therefore in ſtead of loving God, they hate God; as if it were but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded how many times in a day at <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings-gate,</hi> as alſo in all the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> thou ſhalt hear they are educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in little elſe but to blaſpheme the name of our glorious perſonal God, as ſhall be ſeen more at large in the devil his qualification; ſo that deceive not your ſelves, and that becauſe of your beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or greatneſs, no nor for your pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unleſs you be richly clad with that rich Jewel of Faith, for that will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:92988:53"/> who was thy tutor, and the nature of thy education.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III. The devil or ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> his Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and how he is acted forth.</head>
               <p>FOr your better underſtanding of what I ſhall now write, you ſhall finde this matter enſuing divides it ſelf into ſeveral branches, and not onely as touching his thoughts, words and actions, but there are ſeveral diſtinct actings forth of this wicked ſeed in matter of qualification, and yet all makes up but one ſeed as unto its original, even the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as,</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſome of this ſeed you ſhall hear are acted forth to all maner of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yea ſuch as is ſpoken of in <hi>Romans</hi> the firſt, from verſe 21. to the end of the Chapter, <hi>For this cauſe God gave them up unto vile affections, for even their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did change their natural uſe into that</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:92988:54"/> 
                  <hi>which is againſt nature; and likewiſe alſo the men leaving the natural uſe of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, burned in their luſt one towards an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, men with men working that which is unſeemly:</hi> Of theſe ſorts of devils we have among us at this day, and that not onely ſuch that doth take ſhame for what they have done, but rather will maintain ſuch groſs, foul, filthy acts, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſay they, there is nothing that I can think, ſpeak, or do, but God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it; ſo what if I lye with another mans wife, what harm can be in that? I know no evil in ſo doing, for to me all women are but one woman, and this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a man, and that man, I man eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and therefore if I lye with twenty, they are but all one to me, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a free conſent, what fin can be in this? for what hath ſome in <hi>London</hi> ſaid, that it is no more ſin for a man to lye with any woman, then a Cock to tread a Hen, or a Bull to ſerve a Cowe? nay this ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting devil is qualified and acted forth, ſaying, till a man can act ſin as no ſin, he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:92988:54"/> cannot be free from ſin; for thinking this, it is impoſſible for any man to be free from theſe ſins, unleſs he can ſteal, murther and commit adultery as no ſin, then, and not till then, ſay they, thou haſt no power over ſin, and ſo thou encourageſt thy ſelf in all thy impurity, in that, ſaith thou, <hi>to the pure all things are pure,</hi> ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is unclean of it ſelf, but to him that eſteemeth it ſo, not in the leaſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as unto what the Apoſtle ſpake, that <hi>[to the pure all things are pure]</hi> from hence including all maner of filthy acts whatſoever: Now let any of the Seed of Faith judge, if thou art not given over to a reprobate minde to do thoſe things that are not convenient? for as touching this, ſpeak thy ſelf, what convenience doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in any of theſe thy deſtructive acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? for indeed deſtructive they are, both to thy ſelf, and them thou haſt to deal with; witneſs the tears of many a poor virgin-wife, and the ſad miſery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an innocent virgin hath undergone by thy deviliſh temptation, to the loſs of all
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:92988:55"/> her friends, the defilement of her own body, and the eternal hazard of her ſoul, yet all this is juſtifiable in thy reprobate minde, if thou canſt but ſatisfie thy luſt, and ſpend her money, that is all the love that ſhe ſhall finde from thee; and when this pretty deluded creature comes and tells thee how the caſe is with her, I am with childe by thee, and thou haſt ſpent all my money, what wilt thou do with me? wilt thou, according to thy promiſe, make me thy wife, and do thy beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to ſatisfie me for this wrong thou haſt done to me?</p>
               <p>What is his anſwer, think you? even this he will reply: Alas, what can I do for thee? marry thee I cannot, in that I have a wife; and to maintain thee I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, in that I have it not for my ſelf, ſo thou muſt provide for thy ſelf as well as thou canſt: Now if this poor deceived creature [ſhould reply, and ſay] thou tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me thou waſt ſingle, and it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pure love to me, and that thou lovedſt me above all the world, ſo I did
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:92988:55"/> condeſcend to lie with thee, thinking thou wouldeſt make me thy wife, by which I have not onely brought my ſelf to ſhame and beggery, but for ought I know, have damned my ſoul. Upon theſe words this Ranting devil breaks forth, ſaying, A pox take you for a whore, you are a dark de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil indeed, to ſay thou ſhalt be damned for thy love, the Scripture commands us to love our neighbor as our ſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to love our neighbors wives, and how can our love be more expreſt, then in kiſſing, ſporting, and lying one with another? and thus they make <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and his writings their patern, nay, they will engage ſoul for ſoul that ſhe ſhall not be damned, provided ſhe do not look upon it as a ſin; for ſay they, to lye with a maid, widow, or our neighbors wife, is no more then to lye with that woman you call my wife; for I know none lawfully married in this world, but thoſe onely that are one in fleſh and ſpirit, and ſhe that you call my wife, though I have had many children by her, ſhe is but a whore,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:92988:56"/> and the children baſtards, for we were not contracted in this light and purity aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Now let any ſober man judge the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this kinde of devil, that his love and purity is to deſtroy and begger a poor innocent ſoul, and yet plead for it as the onely truth, ſaying, It is not I, but the Lord in me; of my ſelf I can do nothing, and he is all in all, with many ſuch like Scriptures they will produce, for to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their deviliſh luſt, perſwading them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that God is an infinite formleſs Spirit, an infinite Nothing, or an infinite All, in this their beaſtly reaſon, ſo that well comes in that ſaying of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 50. 21. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done, and kept ſilence, thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf;</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, Thou thoughteſt it was I that committed adultery, that did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen and lye with the innocent, thou thoughteſt it was I in thee that moved thee to ſwear, whore, and cheat thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low mortals; but thou ſhalt know that I
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:92988:56"/> am a God, that is not an infinite nothing, for out of nothing, comes nothing; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thou ſhalt know, that I am not an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite All in thy filthineſs, for the day is at hand that I will reprove thee, and that god in thee, as in <hi>Romans</hi> 1. <hi>thou haſt changed the truth of God into a lye,</hi> in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there is no other God but what is in thee, and ſo worſhip me as a God filled with all unrighteouſneſs, fornication, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, covetouſneſs, maliciouſneſs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, murther, debate, deceit, an inventer of all evil things.</p>
               <p>Thus in part you have heard how this ranting devil is qualified and acted forth, and that not onely to all maner of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but man burning in luſt with man, and women with women, as before rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and the more it is to be obſerved, that what they do in this nature, they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it to be juſt, yea to do as they would be done unto, for you that knows them, as much as I, ſhall finde their tongues tipt with theſe and ſuch like words, but in their actions, as you have heard, they have
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:92988:57"/> ſold themſelves to commit wickedneſs, and that with greedineſs, never finding themſelves more happy then when they are a whoring or drinking, which to them is a pure truth as any ſentence in Holy Writ; for they do not eſteem that ſin which the Scripture records for ſin, in that they do not know what to make of that glorious perſonal God nor his writing, looking upon it as a Hiſtory of mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; for, ſay they, the Scripture is a meer Map of Contradiction, ſo that ſuch devils of this kinde in their hearts do not believe it no more then another writing, onely for fear of the Law they will ſay as you ſay, for what do they affirm, A lye and a truth is all one to us, and ſo whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we do, is righteous, juſt and good, and when we die, we ſhall be ſwallowed up into the infinite Spirit, as a drop into the Ocean, and ſo be as we were, and if ever we be raiſed again, we ſhall riſe a horſe, a cow, a root, a flower, and ſuch like, and ſo turn the world round as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; as for hell or damnation it is all here,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:92988:57"/> ſo if they can but eſcape priſon, ſickneſs, and want of money; they fear no other hell or torment hereafter whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Now let any ſober man conſider the devils quality that acts forth this ſort of this curſed ſeed; and as for their language, if there were a devil without man, that had any dealings with man, if poſſible, they would curſe and ſwear that devil out of his name and wits; for ſome of this ſort when they are in company with their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed tribe, what oath or oathes was ever heard by the ear of man, but they have it, and that with authority from their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cain</hi> they maintain it, and that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly from Scripture, and ſo will take oath againſt any one they have a revenge to, if their falſe oath will prevail, they will do it. Thus much of the white, light, ranting devil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next ſort of this curſed feed are qualited and acted forth in moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs like unto the firſt, onely the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is, the white ranting devil doth approve of all his wickedneſs to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:92988:58"/> when this black ranting devil doth judge it a ſin; and yet though his tongue will rayl on the white ranting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and in what company ſoever he comes he will ſpeak againſt theſe curſed actions, and that becauſe he doth not onely know them to be evil, but he is afraid his wife, husband, children, or parents ſhould know of it, and not onely that, but he is afraid the Law will take hold of him, and ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him, if not put him to death for it; theſe and ſuch like are the motives indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him to ſpeak againſt that with his tongue, which his heart burneth and luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after: but however all theſe outward fears attend him, yet this luſt or devil is ſo deſiring after a beautiful maid, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans wife, that though he will ſay it is a ſin, and hath read the wrath of God due for it, yet he will hazard not onely his credit in this world, but the loſs of his ſoul in the world to come; and the ground of this his dangerous attempt, ariſeth from theſe and ſuch like thoughts, I may eſcape as well as others, and I will be ſure
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:92988:58"/> that none ſhall ſee me lye with any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, neither doth any of my neighbors ſuſpect me, ſo that before I will loſe the ſociety of ſuch a rare creature, in whom my ſoul is wholly raviſht with the thoughts of what pleaſures and delights I ſhall have with her, I will hazard both ſoul and body; for what ſaith ſuch a ſort of devil as this? as for the world I will play my cards ſo wiſely, that none ſhall hear or know of it; and though it be a ſin, it is not the greateſt, neither am I the firſt or ſhall be the laſt, and therefore I ſhall make as good ſhift as another, and beſides that, I know that God is a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God, and though in my ſtrength and youth of my body, I do now and then break forth a little, I hope the Lord, if I do but on my death-bed cry him mercy, he will forgive me.</p>
               <p>Ah poor dark deluded ſoul, doſt thou think, that when the righteous, juſt, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart hath much ado to finde mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and yet thou wicked ungodly man thinkeſt it is eaſie for ſuch as thou? no,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:92988:59"/> no: thou ſhalt finde, that as in the ſtrength of nature and health of body, thou haſt ſpent thy time in ſatisfaction of thy luſt, when all that thy pleaſure is at an end, then in a ſmall meaſure ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto thee what thou ſhalt be at the day of reſurrection: for alas poor heart, thou thinkeſt the God of Truth, is like thee, a man of lies, and by thy corrupt petition to turn the will of God, as with a petition thou canſt turn the will of man, but then to thy coſt thou ſhalt finde he is a God that changes not; which in the laſt Chapter I ſhall ſhew thee at large.</p>
               <p>Now to the matter in hand, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy quality and acting forth, in thy Carriage and Language, that from my Seed-ſpring I ſpeak it, if there were a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil without man, as there is not, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil would tremble to behold thy carriage, and hear thy expreſſions; for pride doth ſo much attend thee, that thou knoweſt not how to faſhion thy garment, nor which way to hang thy Cloak upon thee; now being richly clad, thou knoweſt not
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:92988:59"/> well what to think of thy ſelf, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be a god or a man, thy garments ſo glitter, and thy heart ſo proud, and carrieſt thy head ſo high, that the poorer ſort of thy ſeed ſtands cap in hand to thee, yea, gazing after thee, that thou art ſo puffed up with the thought of this, that thou thinkeſt in thy ſelf none in the world like unto thee for beauty and proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo richly adorned with jewels of gold and ſilver, that thou thinkeſt every one that looks upon thee; admires thee; from hence it is thy devil or ſoul is ſo raviſht with the vain glory of this periſhing world, that thou art never better but when thou art abroad ſhewing thy brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with thy ſervants ſtanding bare-head before thee in the open ſtreets; as alſo to your Church you go, and what is the load-ſtone drawing you thither? onely becauſe you would be looked upon as good Church-men, and to have the praiſe of the world, alſo to ſhew your fine rags as aforeſaid, and to ſee and be ſeen who outſtrips thee in apparel, or what new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:92988:60"/> is invented, this, and onely this is the greateſt load-ſtone inviting you; otherways if thou wenteſt to hear ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and thereby become humble for that thy rude carriage and corrupt beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior, then it would appear in thy lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, but thou art ſo much a ſtranger to ſobriety of ſpeech, that upon every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thou haſt theſe and ſuch like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, God damn me I will have my will, the devil take thee for thy pains, what are you made you damn'd whore? I think the devil is in thee: the devil confound me body and ſoul if I be not revenged on thee: the devil rot thee, and the pox of God take thee for a pocky deviliſh whore, by his life, blood, heart and wounds, I will be the death of thee, with many ſuch wretched blaſphemous expreſſions, that the moderate devil doth even tremble to hear the language of this dark ranting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: In theſe not excluding the light ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting devil, but as far over boots and ſhoes are they in theſe and ſuch like curſed lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſo that before I paſs to the next
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:92988:60"/> ſort of the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> I ſhall parly a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with thee about theſe wicked tearms aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Doſt not thou deſire to be ſaved? this I am ſure thou wilt acknowledge, and yet thou calleſt upon God to damn thee, how canſt thou think to be ſaved, when thy tongue will witneſs, that many times thou haſt ſaid, God damn me: and whereas thou ſaith, the devil take thee for thy pains, thou little thinkeſt that thou art that devil. Oh freind, time is coming that thou ſhalt finde, thou, and ſuch as thou art, the onely devil, and therefore for the time remember when ever thou ſaith the devil take thee, then thou muſt take her, or take him, to whom thou uttereſt thoſe words, it is thou devil-man, thy ſelf muſt take them, and when thou ſaith thou art mad, I think the devil is in thee, thou ſpeakeſt truth not knowing it, and ſo when thou ſaith, If I be not revenged of thee, the devil confound me ſoul and body, now if thou be not revenged, as many times thou art not, then thou art
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:92988:61"/> juſtly confounded, and if thou do revenge thy ſelf, thou art alſo confounded, in that thou ſhouldeſt leave that to the Lord; <hi>For revenge is mine, ſaith the Lord</hi> [I will, not thou] I will as I ſee cauſe revenge it, ſo that in this thou haſt ſealed thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; and whereas thou ſaith, the pox of God take thee: ah poor ignorant ſoul, thy tongue declares what a corupt, ulcerated humor doth run in the veins of thy ſoul and body, that thou thinkeſt God like thy ſelf, when he declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a God all holineſs and purity, glorious immortal, that no mortal corruption could in the leaſt touch him; for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Thou wilt not ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption;</hi> and that ſuch a devil as thou ſhalt ſay the pox of God, when it is really and truly the pox of thy devil luſt within thee, as aforeſaid: I told thee how thou wouldeſt hazard not thy credit and eſtate, but thy ſoul alſo, for a beautiful, yet poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key creature in whom, and for whom, thou haſt not onely beggered thy wife and children, but corrupted thy body, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:92988:61"/> thy noſe or thy bowelts rot within thee, and yet thou ſo audaciouſly ſhalt ſay, the pox of God, when it is the pox of a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring luſtful devil thy ſelf, and then in all thy diſcourſe thou muſt ſwear by his life, when thou haſt nothing to do with it, in that his life is death in thee and to thee, for thou hateſt in thy life to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the life of Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take notice thou haſt no ſhare nor benefit in his heart, blood or wounds, it was never ſpilt nor wounded for them that are far better qualified then thou, yet the blood or wounds of the Lord was not for any of the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> but he was onely wounded, and ſpilt his hearts blood for the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> or <hi>Abraham,</hi> that bleſſed Seed of Faith; therefore thou wretched ſoul, let this my ſhort parley with thee, be for ever a <hi>Memento</hi> to look into thy ſoul, and there thou ſhalt finde the devil that tempts or infuſeth thee to utter all this diabolical language; but true is that ſaying in <hi>John,</hi> from the bleſſed tongue of Chriſt, <hi>Ye are of your father</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:92988:62"/> 
                  <hi>the devil, and the luſts of your father ye will do;</hi> for from him to you, comes cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, oathes and lies, who is the father of it: As let but any ſober man obſerve their quality in this, and you ſhall have them ſwear, and ſay, God forgive me whore, and cry, God forgive me: lye, and ſay, God forgive me; thus thou thinkeſt it is nothing, but with one and the ſame tongue ſay and unſay, to lye, cheat, whore, ſwear, and be drunk, and onely ſay, I have ſinned, God forgive me, and ſo commit the like wickedneſs again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and thinkeſt this will ſerve thy turn; but alas for thee, the portion prepared ſhall at the great day lie heavy upon thee, as read <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36, 37. verſes, <hi>I ſay unto you, that every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give account thereof at the day of judgement; for by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned, for out of thy own mouth he will judge thee,</hi> as thou ſhalt read at large in the next Chapter, that ſhall ſhew the place and nature of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils torment.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:92988:62"/>
               <p n="3">3. The next ſort of the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> are qualited and acted forth to all maner of covetouſneſs and worldly mindedneſs, inſomuch that thou abhor a drunkard or any that is given to hoſpitality, and that becauſe his quality is quite contrary to thine; for thou art all for toyling and moyling, riſing early, and lying down late, neglecting no opportunity wherein thou mayeſt enrich thy ſelf, when as the other riſeth up early, and lyeth down late in drunkenneſs, ſpending and making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that portion which was given thee, ſo that thou being covetous, he is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for thee; for thou haſt ſo much care in thee, and upon thee, how to make thy ſelf great on this earth, that unleſs thou canſt advantage thy ſelf, thou wilt not ſpend a penny; but when thou haſt got five pounds, or more, or leſs, then whatſoever ſhift thou and thy family ſhall make, that ſhall not be diminiſhed in the leaſt, but to uſury it muſt go, and then thou pincheſt thy belly, and the bellies of thy poor wife and children, by living ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:92988:63"/> long upon ſmall Beer and flet Cheeſe, and ſuch like ſtuff, that thou increaſeſt thy eſtate to a vaſt ſum at laſt, that now the greateſt care and thought of thy heart is, how thou ſhalt ſecure thy riches from ſome of thy ſeed, that if they ſhould break into thy houſe, they may not plunder thee of it, and to that end thou inventeſt all maner of ſubtilty to deceive the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that thou hideſt ſome in the earth, and ſome on the houſe-top, and ſome in hollow trees, one place or another, that thy brother ſerpent may not ſteal it from thee, or the Law of this thy kingdom im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe great Taxes upon thee; I ſay, thy care is ſo much upon this thy periſhing earthly treaſure, that thy heart, thy ſoul, is wholly wrapt up in it, inſomuch that thy ſleep and meat goes from thee; that now having what thy heart deſireth after, thou art more tormented now then when thou hadſt little or nothing; therefore remember that of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 15. where he ſaith, <hi>Beware of covetouſneſs, for a mans life conſiſteth not in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:92988:63"/> 
                  <hi>of the things which he poſſeſſeth, and where thy treaſure is, thy heart will be alſo;</hi> ſo that what will all this thy greatneſs in this world, and plenty of gold or ſilver avail thee, when the tears of the poor are laid naked before thee, and ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for want of bread, which thou hadſt in abundance? and not onely this, but it is read in thy ſoul, that thou haſt enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſelf in the ruine of others, and thy conſcience tells thee, thou never got this juſtly, but by fraud and deceit, by grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faces of the poor, and keeping back the hire of the laborers. As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, look about you, ye Tradeſmen of all ſorts, yea, from the higheſt to the loweſt, examine your own conſciences how often ye have cheated; and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this ye Landlords, that oppreſs the poor Tenents; as alſo ye Brokers that grinde the faces of the poor, in lending upon uſury, or commodities, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forty or fifty pound in the Hundred; I ſay, remember this, that no cheater, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, nor extortioner ſhall enter into
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:92988:64"/> the kingdom of Heaven, and therefore againſt you I cry wo, wo, wo; for this ſhall riſe up a witneſs againſt thee, and ſhall eat thy fleſh, as if it were fire, as it is in <hi>James</hi> the fifth, the firſt, ſecond, third and fourth verſes, and then, even then, when thou thinkeſt all is well, and that thou haſt ſetled thy eſtate to thy hearts content, that now thou feareſt no want, but canſt without trouble cheriſh up thy ſoul with the fruits of thy wits and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors, and to take thy pleaſure for the time to come, then comes the meſſenger Death, and deprives thee of all the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of thy riches, and ſaith unto thee, <hi>Ah fool, this night thy ſoul ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> Luke 12. 20. Now thou haſt brought thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous heart to perfect what it longed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and now muſt thou leave all, and knoweſt not what will become of thy ſoul on the other ſide of death, and ſo in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and fear of death thou dieſt, and in torment thou ſhalt riſe at the great day,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:92988:64"/> as in the next Chapter thou ſhalt hear and read at large.</p>
               <p>So that I cannot but admire the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful wiſdom of my God, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the pleaſure and pomp of this world belongs onely to the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> yet he gives them a bitter cup to drink at laſt, which potion makes the devil afraid and to tremble at the thought of that day, by which they are not onely bridled from their great cruelty and tyranny they would impoſe upon the Seed of Faith, but alſo the thought of death doth in ſome meaſure out-top their pleaſures and greatneſs, ſo that their life in this their onely heaven, is not much better then our life in this our onely hell; for though they have fulneſs, and ſuch as we have want, yet we have peace, and they have war, yea oftentimes ſad torment to think what will become of their ſouls, when as the Seed of Faith knoweth what he is here, what he ſhall be in the grave, and what he ſhall be at the reſurrection, even glorified with his Savior.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:92988:65"/>
               <p>So if you ſeriouſly lay to heart the vaſt difference of the Seed of Faith, and the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> upon their bed of ſickneſs or hour of death, it would cauſe admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as thus: The departure of the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> out of this world, is as much as if a Prince ſhould depart, not onely from his loving wife and pretty children, but be baniſht from his Crown and Kingdom, never to enjoy it more, and alſo where he is baniſht, he is ſhut up priſoner all the the time of his life, even ſo is his death in this world; he muſt leave, not onely all his ſociety, but the pleaſure of this his kingdom, where he had delight as much as heart could wiſh, and in the grave his ſoul and body lyeth uncapable of either joy or ſorrow, and then at the great day of our Saviors appearance, thou ſhalt be raiſed up thy body thy hell, thy ſoul thy devil, ſhut up cloſe priſoner world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
               <p>Now death is unto the Seed of Faith as a Meſſenger of glad tidings, in that it frees him from the cruelty and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:92988:65"/> of the devill the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> and take him from all his hardſhip and wants that he hath undergone, by living up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly in this ſtrange kingdom, and then he knowing, that all the time he is in the grave, there is no remembrance of good or evil, and as ſoone as ever his God comes, he ſhall be raiſed to meet him in the aire with his mighty angels, where he ſhall have a kingdom that one hours enjoyment of that, will be more then ten thouſand times ten thouſand the greateſt ſubſtance of glory could be attained unto for ten millions of years in this periſhing world. Thus in brief you have the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the two Seeds, what triumph the Seed of Faith have in death over the ſeed of <hi>Cain:</hi> Now to the laſt ſort of this people.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The next and laſt ſort of this ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> you cannot eaſily, neither for carriage nor action, finde them much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the Seed of Faith, nay, in ſome things they outſtrip ſome of the Seed of Faith, as by and by you ſhall
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:92988:66"/> hear: For carriage they are very ſober, and much given to moderation, that they are very temperate both in meat and drink, and modeſt and decent in apparel, and you ſhall not hear an oath from them, unleſs ſome ſmall petty oath, as they call it, <hi>by faith, or troth,</hi> and ſuch like, and that very ſeldom, for thou art acted forth to be mindful of thy tongue, leſt thou ſhouldeſt offend therewith; and for hoſpitality and benevolence, thou art no niggard, but free-hearted to them that thou reſpecteſt; and for private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique duties thou art very obſervant, and in prayer and ſinging of Pſalms, thou wilt many times ſhed tears, and ſigh and groan if thou commit ſome crime againſt the Law, and very vigilant thou art to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thy children in obedience to that God thou knoweſt, and for thy expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they are ſo ſeaſoned with ſugared heaven-like moderation, ſo affable and courteous, that thou wouldeſt, if poſſible, deceive God himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now if you ſay unto me, <hi>How can this</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:92988:66"/> 
                  <hi>ſort of people be any of the ſeed of</hi> Cain? I anſwer: The moderate, hypocritical, Saint-like devil, is of all devils moſt to be ſuſpected; for of this ſort was that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devil that came to tempt Chriſt; he was not onely moderate, as you have him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, but he was well read in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſeemingly holy he behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, otherwiſe he had not by the Prieſts and Rulers been ſent to tempt Chriſt; ſo that I ſhall endeavor to ſatisfie thee in my Anſwer, both from experience and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which ſhall be made plain, that all that cryeth, Lord, Lord, ſhall not enter into the Knowledge of the onely Lord God; for of this ſort of people are theſe, as is recorded <hi>Matthew</hi> 15. 8. <hi>This people draweth nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoreth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me,</hi> however you may think it ſtrange, that ſuch a one that will not ſwear, whore, nor be drunk, nor take the name of God in vaine, but in ſtead of ſpending his time idly, he will be reading the Scripture, &amp; in conference
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:92988:67"/> with good men about the things of God, and in ſtead of walking in the fields on the Sabbath, he will be hearing the word preached, and then in the evening when others are ſitting at door, to ſee and be ſeen, he will be in his chamber at pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and with his whole family ſinging of Pſalms, or ſome ſuch like exhortation, becoming the day, and if thou be an Officer in thy pariſh, <hi>viz.</hi> Conſtable, or Churchwarden, in ſtead of tipling in the Ale-houſe in the Sermon time, thou wilt rather loſe the benefit of that word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and ſpend the time in ſearching and peeping into Ale-houſes, to ſee if thou canſt finde any of thy lewd brethren, to puniſh them for their drunken ſins: this thou wilt do, and that with delight and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>This ſort of people you may admire ſhould be the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> ſo riſe a devil at the laſt day, [what muſt be, muſt be] the Lord knoweth who are his, which with their whole heart walk without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie before him; for as touching this,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:92988:67"/> you ſhall finde thy brother before thee was as careful to ſerve the Lord, as thou canſt be; as read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58. 2. and ſo on, <hi>Yet they ſeek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a Nation that did righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and forſook not the Ordinance of their God: they ask of me the ordinance of juſtice, they take delight in approaching to God.</hi> Doſt thou hear what a heaven-like character the God of Truth gives of thy brethren? and if thou doſt but mind what thou readeſt, thou ſhalt finde five ſpecial remarkable notes of a true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and the firſt is, <hi>they ſeek me daily,</hi> not onely the Sabbath day, but every day. 2. <hi>and delight to know my ways,</hi> what my will and pleaſure is. 3. <hi>they ask of me the ordinance of juſtice,</hi> as though they would do no unjuſt thing. 4. <hi>It was their pleaſure and delight in approaching to God.</hi> 5. <hi>Neither would they forſake the outward Ordinance of God:</hi> But now one word cuts them out for hypocrites, and that becauſe all this that they do <hi>[was but as a Nation] that did righteous things:</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:92988:68"/> in plain tearms, they were not in their heart what was ſhewed by their tongues; for if you read the antecedent verſes, you ſhall finde all this was but to be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by God; for if you minde the third verſe, you ſhall there read their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie at large: and in the fourth and fifth verſes, the all-knowing God repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them for their cheating and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in their hearts; and then in the ſixth and ſeventh verſes, tells them wherein their great error lay, ſaying, <hi>This is the faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy burthens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and that ye break every yoke, is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry? that thou bring the poor that are caſt out, to thy houſe? when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him? and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thy own fleſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the qualities of a true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, not to ſpeak and prate, but to do; for behold, to obey is better then all thy hearing, praying and ſinging, as <hi>James</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:92988:68"/> ſaith, <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works:</hi> Faith is of a doing and working nature; thou ſhalt not of ſuch hear many vain boaſting words, but many merciful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for if you minde that all the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that God denounced againſt the houſe of Iſrael, was for the non-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of charitable actions; as read all the prophets, and where ever you finde the Lord conteſting with ſtrict, great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, it was for neglecting the works of mercy, and therefore he ſaith in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 15. <hi>When ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you, yea, when you make many prayers, I will not hear:</hi> and what is the cauſe, think you? alas, your hands are full of blood, ye do not ſeek judgement, nor reſcue the oppreſſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judge ye the fatherleſs, nor plead for the widow, with thouſands of theſe and ſuch like you ſhall finde, and yet thou makeſt no account of this: for what is thy thought? if I can but carry my ſelf demure with a Saint-like countenance, and go Saint-like in apparel, and carry a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:92988:69"/> heaven-like outſide to the world, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my ſelf civil and moderate in my words, I ſhall do well enough, though I do not thoſe works of mercy ſo much ſpoken of: I ſay ſuch as thou, this is thy thought, and this is thy practice, ſo to conclude, I ſhall refer the moderate ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> to the three and twentieth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> where thou ſhalt read thy inward turn'd outward, yea, the hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and cheat of thy heart laid naked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, for what ever woes thou their readeſt againſt them, that wo concerns thy ſelf: As wo unto thee moderate, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven like Saint, <hi>for thou art like unto the whited ſepulchres, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but within are full of dead mens bones, and of all uncleanneſs; even ſo ye alſo outwardly appear righteous unto men, but within ye are full of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and iniquity:</hi> wo unto thee, for now thou wilt make a trade of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, yea, garniſh the ſepulchres of them as righteous men, and yet at this day will ſpeak evil, impriſon, if not put to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:92988:69"/> death, the true prophets and righteous of the Lord, ſo that ye be witneſſes to your ſelves, that ye are the children of them that murthered the Lord of glory. Ah wo, wo, as thou with the reſt, in the next Chapter ſhalt hear thy doom and endleſs torment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IV. The devil or ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> the place and nature of his torment.</head>
               <p>IN that the face of the Creation is vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with darkneſs and ignorance of Chriſts coming to judge both the quick and the dead, therefore I ſhall treat of this moſt needful point, from certain ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of himſelf, as read <hi>Matth.</hi> 24 where you ſhall finde, <hi>As the light cometh out of the eaſt, and ſhineth even to the weſt, ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Son of man be; and as it was in the days of</hi> Noah, <hi>ſo ſhall it be in the days of the Son of man,</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:92988:70"/> 
                  <hi>they ate, they drank, they bought, they ſold, they married, and were given in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, until the day that</hi> Noah <hi>entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ark, and the flood came and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all: ſo in the days of</hi> Lot, <hi>they ate, they drank,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but in the day that</hi> Lot <hi>went out of</hi> Sodom, <hi>it rained down fire and brimſtone from Heaven, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them all; So the day of the Lord ſhall come as a thief in the night, in which the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the earth alſo and the works tbat are therein ſhall be burnt up,</hi> then ſhall all the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> mourn, tremble and ſhake, when they ſee the Son of man in the clouds of Heaven with power and great glory, yea, at the ſound of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the devil or ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> will cry to the rocks and mountains, <hi>Fall on us,</hi> yea, ye will run into Caves and Cellars to hide your ſelves from the preſence of that glorious perſonal God, whom in your life time ye deſpiſed and rejected, yea, ſcoffing and walking after your own
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:92988:70"/> luſts, ſaying, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his coming, for ſince the Fathers and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning?</hi> and ſo ye ſwear, whore and be drunk, yea, cheat, oppreſs, impriſon and deſtroy the Seed of Faith, not in the leaſt laying to heart that the day of Chriſt Jeſus, that glorious God, is at hand, and will come as a thief in the night, yea, as ſwift as lightening in the air, inſomuch that two ſhall be in the bed, two in the field, two in the mill, or whereſoever two or more are together, they ſhall not have time to ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, till the Lord of glory take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Seed of Faith from the ſeed of <hi>Cain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſure as the Lord liveth, thus it will be very ſuddenly with this proud, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, luſtful, bloody world, that ſport themſelves about the reſurrection of the dead, and the day of Judgement, ſaying it is already paſt, or there will never be any ſuch day; I ſay, before ye be aware of it, Chriſt the King of Glory will open
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:92988:71"/> the firmament of Heaven, and ſtand in the air, with his mighty angels ſurrounding his perſon, and then by the power of his word ſpeaking, as he raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the grave, ſo will he raiſe all the Seed of Faith both dead and alive in the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye, as he did <hi>Elias,</hi> yea in a moment, changing our mortal bodies to immortal, like himſelf; for you read in that day that <hi>Lot</hi> departed out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the ſame day it rained down fire and brimſtone, and deſtroyed them all. Oh what a dreadful and ſudden deſolation fire maketh in a mortal world in one day! ſo ſwift the Lord will appear, that he will make a quick diſpatch, and after all the Seed of Faith, that handful or little flock, are ſafely arrived with him in the air, then the Man Jeſus with a flood of fire, will burn all the beauty and glory of this world to aſhes or dry ſand, leaving behind the ſouls and bodies of the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> then living, with the ſouls and bodies of their dead ſeed raiſed up, burning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like fire and brimſtone upon this
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:92988:71"/> earth, in utter darkneſs. Having in brief, by Reaſon, Faith and Scripture, proved to all ſober-minded men, that a day of Judgement will come, the maner and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its coming, now I ſhall ſhew thee the place where that ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall be tormented, which yet from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till this laſt Witneſs could never be found out, nor any true, infallible deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption given, as touching the place called <hi>Hell,</hi> though moſt of the Learned have attempted, yea ſtretched the line of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the utmoſt, yet all to no purpoſe; for thy father before thee, and thou his learned ſon, art not in the leaſt ſatisfied, and that becauſe thou haſt not the ſeed of Faith, which is the evidence of things not ſeen, therefore being out of the bounds of reaſon, thou writeſt of it thou knoweſt not what, and ſo to finde it thou knoweſt not where; and therefore it is by thee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, that place called <hi>Hell</hi> will be under the earth, in the ſea, or in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of it; if not, thou ſuppoſeſt Hell ſhall be in the air, or a place thou apprehendeſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:92988:72"/> not; therefore from my ſeed-ſpring I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and that thy own experience ſhall finde, that place of thy torment ſhall be even there where thou tookeſt thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that ſhall be the place of Hell, even here in this world, on this earth, where now thou walkeſt, ſhall be the place of thy endleſs miſery.</p>
               <p>For if you obſerve your own rule in the execution of your Law, when a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is apprehended for wilful murther, or ſome ſuch hideous crime, when he is brought to his Tryal, and by your Law found guilty, then the Judge of the Law paſſeth Sentence, that his body ſhall be burned or hanged, even in that place where he committed his bloody, filthy act, and that juſtly where he ſpilt blood, his blood ſhould be required again; even ſo the Lord of Glory, Chriſt Jeſus the Judge of the quick and dead, when he comes to Judgement, all you that have been guilty in the blood of the Prophets, Chriſt Jeſus, and his Diſciples, that have put to death, impriſoned, or any way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:92988:72"/> the Witneſs and righteous of the Lord, that bleſſed Seed of Faith, I ſay, where you executed your oppreſſion and cruelty againſt the ſons of the moſt high God, even there will the righteous Judge execute his fury to take vengeance of all his bloody enemies in this world, in this earth, where thou committedſt thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, thou ſhalt receive thy ſad and dreadful portion, and that world without end; and therefore deceive not thy ſelf with the vain imaginations of thy ſpirit of reaſon, that though it be as I affirm, yet thou hopeſt it doth not belong to thee: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at is the cauſe of thy hopes? thou art neither ſatisfied in thy ſelf, nor doth it appear to any other, onely thou hopeſt with the reſt of thy ſeed, but haſt no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in the leaſt, and that becauſe thou findeſt within thee that thou art guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if not of publick, yet of private filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo that, mark what I ſay, believe it whether thou wilt or no, thou ſhalt by woful experience finde, that this beautiful world wherein now thou haſt thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:92988:73"/> ſhall at the day of Chriſts next ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, be, as aforeſaid, burnt to aſhes or dry ſand, where all the ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> which in his qualification I have branched forth into four particulars, ſhall not need to trouble themſelves about Heaven, and how they ſhall come to it, for as ſure as God is a chryſtal, glorious, holy, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, perſonal God, thou that deſireſt with <hi>Balaam</hi> to die the death of the righteous, and not to live the life of the righteous, thou with all thy pretended holineſs and unrighteouſneſs, ſhalt be raiſed no higher then this earth that now thou treadeſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for as here thou haſt taken thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo here ſhall be thy ſorrow; as here thou haſt been a perſecutor of God and his people, ſo here thou ſhalt have the vengeance of God upon thee, and in thee; as here thou haſt cheated, and burned in thy filthy luſt towards woman, ſo here ſhall thoſe luſtful actions burn in thy ſoul and body for ever; as here thou haſt ſworn and been drunk, ſo here thou ſhalt have nothing to quench thy thirſt, but
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:92988:73"/> even here upon this earth where now thou walkeſt, thou ſhalt howl, burn &amp; fry to all eternity, when then none ſhall pity thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Having ſhewed thee the place where the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall be tormented, now I ſhall ſhew thee the maner and nature of thy torment, and therefore attend &amp; give ear: That after our Redeemer hath called up the Seed of Faith, which are but few in compariſon of what ſhal be left behind, yet I ſay, after he hath taken that little Flock to himſelf, then will our long look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Chriſt Jeſus, the God of Glory, immediately, yea in a few hours, burn all the riches, beauty and bravery of this world to dry ſand, as aforeſaid, inſomuch that there ſhall not be left the leaſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a houſe, herb, tree or plant; for the Stars, Moon and Sun that gave light and motion to the fruits of the earth, and moving of the ſea, ſhall become nothing, yea, be put forth as the ſnuff of a Candle, and this world ſhall be as dark as the land of <hi>Egypt</hi> was for three days; for if you read <hi>Exodus</hi> 10. 22, 23. you ſhall finde
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:92988:74"/> there was a thick darkneſs in all the Land of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> three days, they ſaw not one another, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther roſe any from his place for three days; ſo that after all is burnt to aſhes, and that which gave life and motion to the earth and ſea, is put forth, then ſhall the earth bring forth no more fruit, nor the waters run no more, but become a dark, ſtanding, ſtinking pool, as it was in the beginning, and all the ſeed of <hi>Cain</hi> then both dead and living, ſhall be left behinde with bodies as heavy as lead, and as black as pitch, which then their bodies ſhall be their hell, and their ſpirits or ſouls ſhall be the devil, ſhut up cloſe priſoner together for ever and ever without end; and that fire and brimſtone that will burn, ſhall be thoſe wicked thoughts, words and actions which in thy life time where now thou art, thou committedſt againſt the Seed of Faith, yea with a great hand of pride acted againſt them, ſhall be the fuel, as wood and coal is fuel to the natural fire, ſo thy wicked luſtful actions ſhall be the onely fuel that ſhall burn, yea flame more hotter then any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fire in the hotteſt furnace whatſoever, and yet it ſhall give no light at all, but the flame thereof ſhall be of a durty, ſcalding, burning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious nature, which ſhall ſmoak and fry through thy mouth, thy noſtrils, thy eyes, thy fundament, inſomuch that there ſhall not from the crown of the head, to the ſole of thy foot, be one part
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:92988:74"/> free, but tormented throughout thy whole ſoul and body. And no ſooner hath our God caught up his bleſſed Seed of Faith, but this beautiful world becomes dark duſt or ſand, as aforeſaid; but then, yea even then, begins thy kingdom of darkneſs, wherein thou muſt continue either ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, lying, kneeling, or ſtanding, not being able to move one foot from the place where thou art raiſed, but there being lockt up to all eternity, never to ſee thy own dreadful face, nor the frightful faces of others, their wailing and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting for ever: Conſidering,</p>
               <p>Firſt, as in relation, that thou hadſt ſo many warnings by ſuch poor deſpiſed ones as I, that hath hazared our eſtates, our liberty, yea life and all, by publiſhing ſuch writings, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations from the Lord, that there was no other Devil but ſuch as thou, as now to thy eternal wo, thou cauſt ſet to thy ſeal is too too true, that if thou hadſt not ſhut thy eyes, and ſtopt thy ears, thou mighteſt have foreſeen what now thou feeleſt, and not onely that, but thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſhall flame, in that thou didſt not onely ſlight, ſcoff, and ſcorn ſuch teſtimonies of truth, but thou perſecutedſt it to death, this is one thing that ſhall burn and never be put out.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the remembrance how thou haſt ſpent thy time in this periſhing world, ſhall quicken, and riſe afreſh within thee, as though
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:92988:75"/> they were but then in doing, for from my ſeed-ſpring I ſpeak it, as there is no remembrance of any thing in the duſt, ſo there is no time to the dead in the grave, for the death of <hi>Adam</hi> to his reſurrection, though it be thouſands of years in reſpect to the living, yet to the dead, ſo long ſleep, ſhall be but as one nights reſt, I ſay when thou art awaked, it ſhall be unto thee as no time at all, for though thou haſt lain in the grave a thouſand years more or leſs, yet then it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto thee as though it was but the laſt night, and as thou in relation to thy thoughts, words, and actions died here, ſo afreſh they ſhall riſe with thee either to thy condemnation, or juſtification.</p>
               <p>O then thou light ranting Devil, that died in the living luſt of thy ſoul, to deceive the poor innocent virgin, or virgin-wife, and was never better, then when thou hadſt opportunities to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy own ſoul, in the undoing of others, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading thy ſelf and others it was no ſin; but at this day thou ſhalt know it was a ſin, and that perſonal God which thou in thy life time deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt, will now leave thee to thy luſtful dealing god within thee, where thou ſhalt be damned to all eternity.</p>
               <p>O then thou dark ranting Devil, that died in the pride and ambition of thy heart, ſpending thy time in all wanton wicked ſports and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:92988:75"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
